<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The eating of the body of Christ, considered in its principles. By John Despagne minister of the gospel. Translated out of French into English, by John Rivers of Chaford in Sussex, Esquire.</title>
            <author>Espagne, Jean d', 1591-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 102 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84086</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3257</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1309_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209023</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867933</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867933</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169751</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84086)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169751)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 175:E1309[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The eating of the body of Christ, considered in its principles. By John Despagne minister of the gospel. Translated out of French into English, by John Rivers of Chaford in Sussex, Esquire.</title>
                  <author>Espagne, Jean d', 1591-1659.</author>
                  <author>Rivers, John, of Chaford in Sussex.</author>
                  <author>Beau, Wil.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 128, 128-170, [14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.N. for Anthony Williamson, and are to be sold at the sign of the Queens Arms in Pauls-Church-yard, neer the West end,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A8v signed: Wil. Beau.</note>
                  <note>Text continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 15".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Transubstantiation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169751:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE EATING OF THE BODY OF CHRIST, Conſidered in its PRINCIPLES.</p>
            <p>By JOHN DESPAGNE Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of <hi>French</hi> into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by <hi>John Rivers</hi> of <hi>Chaford</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>T. N.</hi> for <hi>Anthony Williamſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſign of the Queens Arms in Pauls-Church-yard, neer the Weſt end. 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169751:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169751:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The following Lines are part of the</hi> Epiſtle Dedicatory <hi>which the</hi> Author <hi>ſent to a</hi> Prince, <hi>lately deceaſed.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>LORIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S are all the Moveables of the Spiritual Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, all the Doctrines of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion: but the Table of Shew-Bread, the point of the Euchariſt, is one of thoſe three things which the Law hath ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with a Crown of Gold. This is that Bread, which ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained <hi>David</hi> amidſt his military travels. This is that Honey,
<pb facs="tcp:169751:3"/>
which the <hi>Nazarite</hi> of God found out, having rent aſunder the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This is that hidden <hi>Manna,</hi> which is promiſed to the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. After ſo many others which are gone before me, I make plain the way of this <hi>Bethlem.</hi> And in theſe my exerciſes, my ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is, that the Sun may ſtop his courſe to lengthen the victories of <hi>Joſuah;</hi> that at the ſound of his trumpets, the ſtrongeſt Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires may fall down and fill up their trenches; that his Squadrons may ſcale the higheſt Towers; that the Rivers may run back to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Cataracts at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Arke; that the ſword of God may proſper in the hand
<pb facs="tcp:169751:3"/>
of <hi>Gedeon;</hi> that the Stars may fight for <hi>Barak;</hi> that <hi>Zebulon</hi> may triumph over the Ships of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Tharſis.</hi> And that David having ſerved in the Councel of God, may depart hence full of daies, to enter into the joy of his Maſter.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:169751:4"/>
            <head>The Argument and Apology of the Treatiſe following.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know it will be noted with divers names: with Superfluity, with Novelty, with Nullity and Raſhneſs: And at the firſt ſight its brevity will render it contemptible.</p>
            <p>With Superfluity; becauſe men have already wrot ſo much upon this matter, and have digg'd ſo much in this Mine, that it ſeems to be fully exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. Though it be not my deſign to write nothing but
<pb facs="tcp:169751:4"/>
what was ſaid before, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent a Meſs that hath been ſerv'd in ſo many times; that the world hath good reaſon to be cloy'd therewith.</p>
            <p>With Novelty; becauſe I lay ſuch principles, and introduce ſuch matters, as men have not been accuſtomed to ſee in thoſe who handle the point of the Euchariſt.</p>
            <p>With Nullity, becauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unheard of to many, they wil ſeem to be to far fetcht, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing appertaining to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            <p>With Raſhneſs, becauſe I have obſerv'd the errors of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great Doctors, which men
<pb facs="tcp:169751:5"/>
take no notice of. For are we greater then thoſe Patriarchs, who gave us this well, and have drank of it themſelves, and their children, and their flocks?</p>
            <p>Truly, I reverence thoſe vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Champions, unſheathing the ſword of the Spirit, who environ the bed of <hi>Salomon,</hi> whoſe pillars be of ſilver, and coverings of purple. But ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting their birthrights and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prerogatives, although their wiſdom be of as large an extent as the ſand of the Sea, they have not drained the Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. They themſelves have not thought they have ſaid all, nor to be perfect in what they have
<pb facs="tcp:169751:5"/>
ſaid. We have not yet ſurroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> nor meaſured its towers, nor counted all its battlements. Of the plentiful harveſt of theſe rich men, may remain ſome eares, which we may be permitted to glean.</p>
            <p>As for the Novelty which men will charge me with, I know that many, ſeeing Jeſus Chriſt walk upon the Sea, and not the common way, do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judg it forthwith to be a viſion: But it is not the tree of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit, but the true tree of life, whereto I have faſtned my Meditations. I open no new Springs in the deſert; 'tis a long time ſince they were broached.
<pb facs="tcp:169751:6"/>
If they are new to any, they ought not to complain that they are ſhew'd unto them. By my language I ſhall be taken for a <hi>Galilaean.</hi> It is all that I can fear, and all that I do deſire.</p>
            <p>As for other cenſures, I ſhall anſwer them in the Treatiſe it ſelf. As I have built upon the inſtitution of the ſupper, ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo have I promoted nothing which anſwers not this foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which to verifie there's no need to aſcend into heaven, nor deſcend into the bottomleſs pit. The materials which I employ in this ſtructure, are to be found in the very words of Jeſus Chriſt, inſtituting this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb facs="tcp:169751:6"/>
Theſe words are neer us, and in our mouth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt Sect</hi> prepares us the entrance to them. The <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> meaſure them. The <hi>Third</hi> conſiders the circumſtances of the Euchariſt; its reſemblance to the Paſſover; their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and ſome queſtions which concern them. The <hi>Fourth</hi> touches ſome points of a Chriſtians practiſe in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter In the <hi>Fifth</hi> I give certain general addreſſes, which ſerve not only for the underſtanding of the point of the Supper, but of the whole New-Teſtament alſo.</p>
            <p>In ſum; men will finde that
<pb facs="tcp:169751:7"/>
theſe doctrines are as ancient as the words of Jeſus Chriſt in the Supper, ſith, that they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained there. In this regard, and laying aſide what there is of mine own, <hi>I</hi> may ſay that here are the mountains of incenſe. It is nothing but myrrhe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loes: they are nothing but pearls and carbuncles. Here is that well-furniſht chamber, in which our Maſter celebrated his Paſſover: It is here that we ſhall enter, as it were croſs a cloud, to ſee the wonderful things of the Sanctuary.</p>
            <p>I regard not thoſe who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect rather the quantity of the paper, then the quality of the
<pb facs="tcp:169751:7"/>
work; who eſteem rather of the greatneſs of a Flint, then the Beauty of a Diamond It were as eaſie for me, as for many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to produce a volumn ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with words, and ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with allegations. But 'tis not my end to enlarge my Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacteries This is to abuſe time, and wander out from the way where one may go ſtrait out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right: Eſpecially, ſith, I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake no compleat and entire Treatiſe of the Euchariſt, but onely a ſupplement of that which ſeems to want in other Authors, who have wrot upon this ſubject.</p>
            <p>Finally, although I am not
<pb facs="tcp:169751:8"/>
that learn'd Scribe in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, who draws, from the Treaſure of his heart, things both ancient and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern<hi>:</hi> I hope nevertheleſs to pleaſe thoſe whom ignorance or paſſion hath not prepoſſeſs'd, and their approbation will give me wings to paſs to other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:169751:8"/>
            <head>To his Friend the Tranſlator, on the Subject of his Book.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1</head>
               <l>WHAT ſtricter Jews durſt not aſſay,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>Beaſts</hi> we now convay</l>
               <l>(Miſpriſing the Moſaick Rites,)</l>
               <l>Into our licenc'd Appetites.</l>
               <l>Our Stomacks are our Altars; All Daies, Feaſts;</l>
               <l>To ſacrifice the blood of ſlaughter'd Beaſts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2</head>
               <l>What Heathens moralliz'd would hate,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mans fleſh</hi> with greedy mouthes we eat;</l>
               <l>And then we breath forth pureſt Notes,</l>
               <l>When firſt <hi>Mans blood</hi> has ſmooth'd our throates.</l>
               <l>Our Stomaks are grown ſtronger; and we can</l>
               <l>Digeſt th' unſodden fleſh and blood of Man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>3</head>
               <l>What <hi>Cannibals</hi> could not devour,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Blood</hi> of very <hi>God</hi> we pour</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon our guiltleſs Tables; where</l>
               <l>Nor blood nor fleſh of God we ſpare.</l>
               <l>Digeſtion is ſublim'd; Our inward fire</l>
               <l>Concocts what Cherubs did, and do, admire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <pb facs="tcp:169751:9"/>
               <l>Th' old Childiſh Jew ſo long is ſchool'd</l>
               <l>By th' Law his Pedagogue, till fool'd.</l>
               <l>The meerly Moralliſt ſtill Shrinkes</l>
               <l>At th' fanſie of our horrid Drinkes.</l>
               <l>Yet we keep on our Dyet. Our dry Soules</l>
               <l>Drink their own <hi>Healthes</hi> in blood from th' hallow'd Bowles.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>WIL. BEAU.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169751:9"/>
            <head>The Eating of the BODY of CHRIST Conſidered in its PRINCIPLES.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>The Firſt Sect.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To what the Inſtruction of Chriſtians is now reduced, as concerning the Point of the Supper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of an abuſe which is found in many Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines treating of the Hiſtory of the Paſſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of many circumſtances of the Paſſion, of which we are ignorant of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Cauſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this day more ſtudied, and peradveuture leſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood among the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon ſort of Orthodox Divines, then that of the Euchariſt. Men learn nothing of it but what
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169751:10"/>
reaches to controverſie; as if all the Doctrin of this Sacrament conſiſted in that. To this very end many la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to inform themſelves of nothing but of the belief of the Fathers; as if it were belonging to the purpoſe of the Supper, to know the opinion of <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> or St <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> Let this be ſpoken without diminiſhing the praiſe of thoſe who have ſo profitably Wrote of this Controverſie. It is indeed neceſſary in theſe times; but it is not that which nouriſhes the Soul. A man who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the holy Supper, ought at that time to think of other things, then to reaſon with himſelf whether accidents may ſubſiſt without a Subject; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no mice can eat the Body of Chriſt, whether Tranſubſtantiation were before the Councel of <hi>Verceil</hi> or <hi>Lateran;</hi> and other ordinary queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Or to diſpute Philoſophically upon the words of Concomitance, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, Circumſcriptively, and ſuch like Tearms.</p>
                  <p>Many alſo ſtudie Tracks of Piety
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169751:10"/>
on the Subject of the Supper, in the moſt part of which we may behold much diſcourſe, but little matter: Or if there be ſome ſubſtance, it is but the Rudiments and Alphabet of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, amplified with a multitude of words. In ſuch ſort, that, after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving read a hundred ſuch books which are cryed up among the people, we ſhall finde heaped together much ſpeech, but little Doctrin. They who greatly eſteem them, deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in many reſpects.</p>
                  <p>I muſt advertiſe them of one abuſe which cannot be diſſembled. Wee have ſome Writers who cauſe Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors to paſs for Myſteries, and alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of words for very real matters, yea for demonſtrative Reaſons. When they treat of the Paſſion of Chriſt (which is the true Subject of the Holy Supper) with its particulars and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, behold how they ſpecifie unto us the Cauſes<hi>!</hi> If they ſpeak of the kiſſing of <hi>Judas,</hi> they ſeek the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from the mouth of <hi>Adam,</hi> who
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169751:11"/>
ſinned with his lips. If there be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of the Reed which was put into the hand of Chriſt; it is (ſay they) to ſhew, that he breaks not the bruiſed Reed. If they talk of his Veſtments which were divided into four parts; they tell us they are the four parts of the World, to whom our Lord hath communicated his bleſſings. That he was ſtripp'd of his Garments, is as much as that one day he will reſtore the Kingdom to God his Father. If they diſcourſe of his Purple Robe, it is becauſe he wipes away our ſins which are as red as Scarlet. If he were pierc'd in the Side, it is to the end that wee ſhould have him near our heart. If he were ſmoat on the face, it is as much as that we have disfigured our face, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the Image of God. Oh ſubtill Imaginations<hi>!</hi> Such allegories are tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable in an Oratoricall Diſcourſe, but certainly they are impertinent and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſive when there is queſtion made of teaching exactly. This Style, inſtead of framing a diſtinct and articulated
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169751:11"/>
voice, produces not hing but a confuſed and extravagant noiſe; holding the minds of men in a childiſh ignorance, and rendring the moſt important mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion contemptible and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous; Yet nevertheleſs, the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ſort finde theſe Conceits to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry high, and take them for very ſolid Doctrins and currant money.</p>
                  <p>It is to be noted that many labour in vain to give a particular reaſon of all the Circumſtances of the death of Chriſt. Certainly many of them have their Cauſes pointed out by the very finger of God. That our Lord was faſtned to the wood; That he was lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up; That he ſuffered among thieves; That the place of his puniſhment was without the City; That they caſt lots upon his Garments; That his bones were not broken; That his ſide was pierced; That his hands and his feet were boared through; That Gall was given him to drink, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularities have their alluſion to ſome Oracle, or to ſome Figure which hath
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169751:12"/>
preceded them, from whence may be drawn Theologicall demonſtrations. But as for other Circumſtances, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſpecial reaſons are not taught in the Scripture, or verified by certain analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, it ſufficeth to conſider them ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply as parts of the humiliation of Chriſt, and carry them up to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral cauſes of his Paſſion. Otherwiſe 'tis as much as to feed on imaginarie meats.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of an Uſual expreſſion among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſubject to evill Conſequences.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Have yet this to give advertiſement of; That, in the common language of Chriſtians, there is a form of ſpeech touching this matter of the Supper, in which we ought to uſe no little caution. As for example<hi>:</hi> We ſay ordinarily; The Altar of the Croſs; The Croſs is the Altar (ſay we) on which Chriſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169751:12"/>
was ſacrificed. This phraſe is autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized by the pen of many excellent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors: But we muſt know that their end hath been to apply themſelves to the Vulgar. For they are not ignorant that (to ſpeak properly) the Croſs was not the Altar of the Sacrifice of Chriſt. Otherwiſe this ſpeech would be dangerous for thoſe that know not its importance. And if we ſhould di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute againſt a <hi>Jew,</hi> he would force us to diſavow it.</p>
                  <p>It is a Rule of Divine Right <hi>(Exod.</hi> 29. 37. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 18, 19.) That the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar is more excellent then the Offering. The reaſon is, becauſe the Offering is ſanctified by the Altar. Whereupon we ought to obſerve, that the ancient Fathers, giving the name of Altar to the Table of the Lord, ſhew, that they mean not there to ſacrifice the Body of Jeſus Chriſt for the expiation of ſins. For an Altar of wood or ſtone doth not ſanctifie the Body of our Lord. Therefore they ſo call the holy Table; but not in a ſenſe that doth in any wiſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169751:13"/>
favour Tranſubſtantiation, or the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendances thereon. Finally, it is true that Jeſus Chriſt was offered on the Croſs, but it is falſe that it was held for an Altar in the act of this venerable Sacrifice.</p>
                  <p>For 1. This wood on which Jeſus Chriſt ſuffered, did it ſanctifie the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of his Body? Was the Croſs more excellent or more holy then the Sacred body of the Sonne of God? 2. Add to this, that the Croſs was a mark or token of malediction; <hi>(Gal.</hi> 3. 13.) a quite contrary quality from that of the Altar, which is to bleſs and to ſanctifie. 3. Alſo the holy Scripture, ſpeaking of the ſame Croſs on which our tranſgreſſions were expiated, never gives it the Title of Altar: and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt always abſtains from this phraſe, although that, in many places of the New Teſtament, it ſeems to come much to the purpoſe. 4. Men ſpeak very inconſiderately, to ſay that the Altar of Burnt-Offerings, or that of Incenſe did repreſent the Croſs on
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169751:13"/>
which Jeſus Chriſt ought to be ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. There is more appearance, that the Croſs, on which Jeſus Chriſt was put, was ſignified by the wood on which they placed their Victims. And indeed <hi>Iſaac,</hi> carrying the wood on which he was to be ſacrificed, was a figure of Jeſus Chriſt bearing the Croſs on which he was to die.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. III. <hi>What is the Subject of the thoughts which Chriſtians ought to have when they receive the holy Supper. The Spiritual preſence ill underſtood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Vulgar.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TWo men ſhall produce an action of the ſame kind and the ſame quality, in which nevertheleſs the one hath more noble thoughts then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And for example; both may give Almes with like ſincerity of heart,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169751:14"/>
equall meaſure of charity, and with the ſame reſentment of affection, and yet nevertheleſs in this act one carries more fair and rich conceptions. So among many Chriſtians, who receive the Sacrament by faith, and are carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this action by motions tending to ſalvation, there are ſom whoſe thoughts ſurpaſs thoſe of others, being more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime and compleat, and ſo of a higher dignity, and which render them nearer to the boſome of Jeſus Chriſt. Now the moſt excellent thoughts, which a Chriſtian, communicating at the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, can have, are thoſe which Jeſus Chriſt had and did ſuggeſt unto us in this action, expreſſing them in words full of an incomparable richneſs. To know then what cogitations are there required, the words of Jeſus Chriſt rightly underſtood, will furniſh us with the Subject of them. But ſuch a one preſumes beſt to underſtand them, who is not yet topick enough in every point appertaining to this matter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:169751:14"/>
For I let alone the ſuperficial intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence; wherewith Ideots content themſelves. When they can ſay that as the bread nouriſhes our bodies, ſo the fleſh of Chriſt nouriſhes our ſouls; they think they know enough. Even ſo many do very ill underſtand this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual preſence of Chriſt that is now ſo much diſputed of. Then, when they preſent to themſelves a man nailed to a Croſs, they imagin by this Idea Chriſt is made preſent to their thoughts and that in this act conſiſts the participation of the body of Chriſt. 'Tis true, we cannot call to mind his death and the manner of it, but by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving ſuch an object, namely a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane body, as it is painted in the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Paſſion; his ſide being pierced, and the bloud ſtreaming from the wound, &amp;c. But all this is but an hiſtorical repreſentation, much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the ſpiritual communion of the body of Chriſt. For when I repreſent unto my ſelf Jeſus Chriſt dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Croſs in the moſt lively
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169751:15"/>
manner poſſible for me to do; this fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure or image, which I have in my mind, is not all this while Jeſus Chriſt himſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. III. <hi>A Brief of all that men teach touching the Point of the Lords Supper.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ALL that we conſider in this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, is reduced principally to theſe things. <hi>The divers</hi> names by which this Sacrament is called. <hi>Its Inſtitution</hi> and the time of it. The <hi>two Signes</hi> employed at this Table, and the Cenſure of thoſe who deny the Cup to the people. The <hi>Analogie</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Bread and the Body of Chriſt; between the Wine and the Blood; The breaking of the one and the powring forth of the other, with their ſignification. The <hi>Thankſgiving</hi> or bleſſing by which Jeſus Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated theſe Elements. The <hi>diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:169751:15"/>
between the corporal reception of the ſigne, common both to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and the wicked, and the Spirituall Communication of the Body of Chriſt peculiar to believers. The <hi>examining</hi> of theſe words, wherein we finde that there is a Figure; the name of the thing ſignified being attributed to the Signe, according to the ordinary cuſtom of Sacramentall locutions. <hi>That</hi> the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Signes remain entire. <hi>That</hi> the Body of Chriſt is not encloſed in the Bread of the Euchariſt, nor in any place of the earth. <hi>That</hi> this bodily preſence is not requiſit to the true and reall Communication of it. <hi>That</hi> this Communion is made by the efficacy of the Spirit, on the behalf of Chriſt; and by the Organ of Faith, on our part. <hi>That</hi> this Faith reacheth even unto Heaven, and doth truely joyn us unto Chriſt. <hi>That</hi> the end of this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not there to make an Expiatory Sacrifice, but a Commemoration of him. <hi>That</hi> this Commemoration is not idle and vain, but full of efficacy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169751:16"/>
and affection. <hi>That</hi> the Supper is unto us a Seal of a new Covenant; an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of our Reſurrection; a tye of our Union with the Church, and a Badge of our Profeſſion. To theſe are joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the precepts which ſhew the prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory Exerciſes; the examination which every one ought to make of himſelf, for to partake worthily of it; and finally the acknowledgement or thankſgiving which we ought to make for it.</p>
                  <p>But, as this matter is now almoſt all reduced to controverſie, the moſt part of thoſe who undertake an exact de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of all that may be ſaid upon the Point of the Euchariſt, do make ſtop principally at thoſe things which are in diſpute. And in this regard it is a hard matter to add to their writings, having there neither queſtion which they have not diſcuſſed; error which they have not encountred; difficulty which they have not cleared; ſyllable which they have not culled; argument which they have not preſſed; objection
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169751:16"/>
which they have not diſſolved. But we ſhall find that we may yet bring hither many other important conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and without which this Doctrin cannot be compleat.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Obſervations extracted out of the</hi> Jews <hi>Liturgie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THey, who have read the Books of the Rites of the ancient <hi>Jews,</hi> have drawn from them ſome lights, which ſhew the reaſon of many particulars expreſſed in the Inſtitution of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. For the proceeding of Ieſus Chriſt in the Euchariſt, anſwers to that which the <hi>Hebrews</hi> obſerve in the Paſſeover. Now beſides the Divine Laws which preſcribe the form of this ſacred Feaſt; the <hi>Jews</hi> had Rules for thoſe Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances which were not mentioned in the Law. As for example: <hi>Moſes</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving pronounced nothing touching the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169751:17"/>
Drink of this Solemn Feaſt, their Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Canons ordained that which was convenient for the Action. They relate therefore among the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Formalities of this Banquet.</p>
                  <p>That at the beginning the Maſter of the houſe took the Cup, and, prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God, cauſed it to paſs from hand to hand, to the end that all who ſat at the table might taſt of it. Thus Saint <hi>Luke</hi> relates, that Ieſus Chriſt began his laſt ſupper.</p>
                  <p>That after that, he took bread in his hands, and bleſſing the Divine Majeſtie, brake it, and then gave it to every one that was preſent at the banquet, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, that it was the bread which their fathers had eaten in <hi>Egypt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That for the Cloſe of the Repaſt, he took again the Cup, and preſenting the Wine, ſaid, that it was the fruit of the Vine and the blood of the Grape. Terms borrowed of the old Teſtament <hi>(Gen.</hi> 49. 11. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 14.) and to which our Saviour made alluſion, when, giving the Wine, he ſaid, that it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169751:17"/>
was Blood. Whereupon is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in what the laſt Cup is different from the firſt. Alſo why Chriſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not the Wine and Bread both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, but the bread by it ſelf a-part, and ſo the Wine.</p>
                  <p>That in this Feaſt there was a Diſh compoſed of Rayſins and other Fruits bruiſed and beaten together, ſeaſon'd with vinegar and made clammie like unto clay (in remembrance of the Bricks of <hi>Egypt)</hi> wherein they dipp'd their bread. It may be, it was the platter wherein <hi>Judas</hi> his ſop was dip'd.</p>
                  <p>That the waſhing of Feet, frequent among thoſe of the Eaſt, was not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd at the end of all Feaſts, but only in that of the Paſſeover. From thence it comes, that after Supper Ieſus Chriſt waſhed the feet of his Diſciples.</p>
                  <p>That their Cuſtom was to cloſe this Action with the ſinging of Pſalmes, the 113, and the 114. which is without doubt that Hymn which Ieſus Chriſt and his Diſciples ſang before they went forth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:169751:18"/>
That ſpeaking of the Paſſeover, they oftentimes give it a name which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies <hi>Annunciation,</hi> which is the Term which St <hi>Paul</hi> transfers to the holy Supper, when he ſaith, Ye ſhall <hi>Shew</hi> the Lords death.</p>
                  <p>Without theſe obſervations drawn from the Eccleſiaſtical diſcipline of the <hi>Jews,</hi> it is impoſſible to attain to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect underſtanding of the actions of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt in the Inſtitution of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt. But the ſence of his words, touching his Body and his Blood, ought to be drawn from a higher Fountain.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Neceſſary ſuppoſitions for the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the words of Jeſus Chriſt in the Supper.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THat which Ieſus Chriſt ſaid touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Communion of his Body and of his Blood, all that (I ſay) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169751:18"/>
on certain Maximes, which our Lord hath laid for a Baſis and Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Communion. Now there are very few people which obſerve theſe ſuppoſitions, without which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe it is impoſſible to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand fully the Terms of the Son of God, and to know the importance of them.</p>
                  <p>The words of the Inſtitution adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe us that this Sacrament is a New Covenant (in as much as it is the Seal of it) and by conſequence, that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, or preſuppoſes articles quite new, quite different from thoſe which are contained in the old.</p>
                  <p>For we muſt know that the old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, ſpeaking of the Blood of the Covenant, of the effuſion of it for the remiſſion of ſins, and of the fleſh of the expiatory Sacrifice (Symboles of the Body and of the Blood of Chriſt) did contain certain Ordinances which prohibited that which Ieſus Chriſt commands us in the Euchariſt. Let us retain this carefully. That which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169751:19"/>
the Son of God commands us to do in the Supper, is founded upon Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imes oppoſit to thoſe of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And in this oppoſition conſiſts the Foundation and the Life of the words of Ieſus Chriſt. I conclude then that it is impoſſible, without the conferring of theſe clauſes carried through the two Teſtaments, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue exactly the myſterious words of the Inſtitution.</p>
                  <p>Further, Let not men think that here I mean to bring in Allegories. For the relations and differences between the old and new Teſtament are not Allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall. And if any one will call them by that name, let him know, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch Allegories he ſhall never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand perfectly what Ieſus Chriſt had a minde to ſay. For theſe words, the <hi>Teſtament,</hi> the <hi>Blood</hi> of the <hi>Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> the <hi>Eating</hi> of the <hi>Fleſh given for us; the effuſion of Blood for the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſins;</hi> are terms of the <hi>Moſaicall</hi> Law. It is therefore neceſſary to learn that, which the Law ordained touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169751:19"/>
the communication of the Fleſh and Blood deſtined to the expiation of ſinners, and compare this Ordinance with that of Ieſus Chriſt in the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
                  <p>This will furniſh me with an anſwer to thoſe, who would impoſe upon me to have here introduced matters eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from the ſubject of the Euchariſt, under colour of being far removed from their own thoughts. The conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations which I have to produce, are immediately faſtened to the words of the holy Supper, and ſhew to what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Ieſus Chriſt had regard unto in pronouncing them, as we ſhall ſee here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. On the contrary, many treat of the Euchariſt, who imbroyle it with an infinite number of other points, whilſt they omit a good part of the true ſubſtance of the Sacramentall words, whereof they never expreſſe the entire ſence. None here refuſeth to hear ſpoken of <hi>demon ſtrative pronounes,</hi> of a <hi>verb ſubſtantive,</hi> of a <hi>ſubject,</hi> and of an <hi>attribute,</hi> of <hi>ſynecdoches,</hi> of <hi>Metano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes,</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:169751:20"/>
and other ſcholaſtick Terms, which ſerve only for the grammaticall underſtanding. Why then ſhall the proper names of things which Ieſus Chriſt aimed at in the Euchariſt, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted ſtrangers in this matter? The new Teſtament and the old; the blood ſhed for our ſin, and the blood of le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall expiations; the eating of the fleſh of Chriſt, and the eating of offerings, are terms correlative in the words of the Euchariſt, and do anſwer one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a loud voice. The under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the one depends on the knowledge of the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>A preparatory queſtion to the following Conſiderations.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THere is none but knowes, that our Saviour explained himſelf more formally when he ſpoke of his blood, in preſenting the Cup; and when he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169751:20"/>
ſpoke of his body, in giving the bread<hi>:</hi> For theſe laſt words expound the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and teach us in what quality his body is produced unto us, and given in the Euchariſt; namely, in as much as it is the ſacrifice of the new Teſtament offered for the remiſſion of our ſins.</p>
                  <p>Now theſe words expreſſe the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and the cauſe of our Communion with him: For it is not enough to know that we have the body of Chriſt to eat, and his blood to drink: we ought to know the reaſon and the vertue of it. Otherwiſe we ſhall never underſtand the point of the Euchariſt. This rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is manifeſt. Our Saviour in the 26 <hi>chapter</hi> of St <hi>Matthew,</hi> ſpeaks thus touching the Cup, <hi>Drink ye all of it: For this is my blood of the new Teſtament, which is ſhed for many for the remiſſion of ſins.</hi> But there are but few who know the meaning of Ieſus Chriſt, and wherein conſiſts the knot and connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his purpoſe, That we ought to drink his blood, <hi>Becauſe</hi> it is the blood of the new Teſtament, ſhed for the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169751:21"/>
remiſſion of our ſins. And likewiſe why from the oblation of his body do we conclude the eating of it? What is the conſequence of the one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Here we have many excellent myſteries contained in theſe words of Ieſus Chriſt to diſcover.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:169751:21"/>
               <head>The Second Sect.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The firſt Conſideration on the words of Jeſus Chriſt in the Supper.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>DIvines affirm that Ieſus Chriſt, knowing the Law which forbids eating of blood, hath expreſly menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned a new Covenant which obligeth us to drink his blood. In which he maketh the two Teſtaments to oppoſe one the other. The one which forbids the eating of blood, the other which commands the drinking of blood.</p>
                  <p>But I obſerve one point which is not ſo common, although very notable, touching the reaſon by which Ieſus Chriſt invites us to drink his blood.</p>
                  <p>There is a Law in the 17 of <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus, verſe</hi> 11, and 12, which we muſt compare with the Ordinance of Ieſus Chriſt in the 26 of Saint <hi>Matthew.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:169751:22"/>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>The Law ſaith,</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Jeſus Chriſt ſaith,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>I have given you the blood to offer upon the Altar, to make an atonement for your ſouls: for it is the blood which ſhall make an atonement for the ſoul. It is ſhed for the remiſſion of ſins, and therefore I ſaid to the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> none among you ſhall eat blood.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Drink ye all of it. For this is my blood of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is ſhed for many for the remiſſion of ſins.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Compariſon ſhewes that Ieſus Chriſt commanding to drink his blood, imploys the ſame reaſon for which it was forbidden to eat any blood at all. The Law ſaith, eat no blood; for it is ſhed for the remiſſion of your ſins. Jeſus Chriſt ſaith; drink blood; for it is ſhed for the remeſſion of your ſins. It is then expedient for us to drink his blood for the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which ſeems to forbid it us.</p>
                  <p>From whence comes it, that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169751:22"/>
of the Law and the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of Chriſt are found to be built on the ſame foundation? Why doth the ſame cauſe which obligeth men to abſtain from blood, oblige us to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate of it? How can one and the ſame reaſon ſerve to two contraries? that it ſhould be forbidden to eat blood, becauſe it is expiatory; and commanded to drink the blood becauſ it is expiatory?</p>
                  <p>Some will tell us, that we muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between blood and blood; between that of Chriſt and that of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving creatures; between the ſpirituall perception of the one, and the corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral eating of the other; between the typical expiations, and the reall expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. That <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake of a blood which was but a Seal and Symbole of expiaation, and on the contrary, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt propoſes unto us a blood by which expiation hath been made. That the one ſpeaks of an eating which was done by the mouth; the other of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception which is in the ſoul; And that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169751:23"/>
thus they are two different reaſons. But all this takes not away the difficulty; the queſtion remains ſtill<hi>:</hi> For behold what I have to ſay thereupon.</p>
                  <p>The Law forbids to partake of blood, becauſe it is the ſeal of the remiſſion of ſins. And Jeſus Chriſt commands to partake of the cup, becauſe it is the ſeal of the remiſſion of ſins. Why do two ſo contrary conſequences reſult from the ſame quality The precedent diſtin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction hath no place here.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, we muſt know that the Law, ſpeaking of the blood of living creatures, which it ſays to be expiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, conſiders this blood in the union or correſpondence it hath with that of Chriſt, which alone is truely expiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. So that forbidding the corporall eating of the ſigne that hath relation to the blood of Chriſt, the ſame for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding touches the ſpiritual Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the blood of Chriſt repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſigne.</p>
                  <p>Truely the tearms by which they expreſſe the cauſe of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169751:23"/>
are equivalent to thoſe by which the Law expreſſeth the reaſon of the prohibition. And 'tis not without ſome great reaſon that the Son of God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding to drink his blood, would ſpeak as the Law doth when it prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits the eating of blood.</p>
                  <p>We ſhall therefore ſee from whence is derived this injunction on us to drink the blood of the new Covenant, by the ſame reaſon which forbids us to eat that of the old. But for as much as this queſtion is linked with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther points, we ought to propoſe them conjoyntly, before we diſſolve the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties. Behold then another which ought carefully to be conſidered, as being the center of this matter, and the laſt of the words of Ieſus Chriſt in the Supper.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:169751:24"/>
                  <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The Second Conſideration upon the words of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVE ſpeak of eating the Body which was given for our ſins. Many Orthodox Divines have theſe terms in their mouths, who know not their importance, nor to what Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt had regard in uttering them.</p>
                  <p>It is a RULE in the old Teſtament, <hi>That a man cannot eat of that which is offered for him for the remiſſion of his ſins.</hi> It is, I ſay, <hi>a point of Divine Right, and a fundamentall clauſe of the firſt Teſtament. That none can eat of that which is offered for the remiſſion of his ſins. The ſame fleſh cannot be our attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and our nouriſhment.</hi> Theſe are terms which the Law declares incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible. And nevertheleſs againſt this Maxime, Ieſus Chriſt commands us to eat his Body Sacrificed for our ſins;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169751:24"/>
his body, I ſay, repreſented by expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory oblations, whoſe eating was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden. This here is one of the higheſt myſteries of Religion, and the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacrament of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt.</p>
                  <p>Every one knowes that the old Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament had two ſorts of Sacrifices, diſtinguiſhed by the ends to which they were offered; The one the <hi>Euchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick;</hi> the other the <hi>Expiatory.</hi> The one for the <hi>Benefits of God;</hi> the other for the <hi>Evil deeds of man.</hi> Now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Euchariſtick Sacrifice, all thoſe, for whom it was by name offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, had a right alſo to eat of it. This meat, ſanctified by the Altar and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from common nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, was a moſt favoury Meſs unto them, as being ſent from Gods Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for an earneſt of that Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they had with him. And we even there meet with an admirable cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with the ſubject of the holy Supper. For, by the Rule of the Law, the fleſh of ſuch Sacrifices ought
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169751:25"/>
to be eaten either the ſame day it was ſacrificed, or the day after. But on the third day it was not permitted to eat of it. It is an axiome of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>That no Sacrifice ſhould be eaten on the third day, Levit.</hi> 7. <hi>verſe</hi> 16, 17, 18. This Law ſeems to have an eye upon the eating of the fleſh of Chriſt; which is meat to us, in as much as dead for us. For he exhibits unto us his body; but in as much as broken. So that the object of this eating is Jeſus Chriſt, in as much as dead. Now for as much as the third day, which is that of his Reſurrection, repreſents him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us living, the Sacrifices, by which he was repreſented dead, might not be eaten the third day.</p>
                  <p>But the Sacrifice which was offered for the expiation of ſins, was yet of a higher dignity, and much more myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. In this action Jeſus Chriſt was the entire body of the <hi>Figure,</hi> and was there repreſented more to the life. And the fleſh of this ſacrifice is honoured with a Title which is not given to the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169751:25"/>
other. For 'tis ſaid, that it was moſt holy. An Epithite, which, according to the Stile of the Law, ſignifies not only a ſuperlative degree in this quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but expreſſeth abundance of effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie which it had (by divine inſtitution) to ſanctifie thoſe who eat of it, <hi>Levit.</hi> 6. 27. But (that which is carefully to be obſerved) none of thoſe for whoſe ſin it was offered, had permiſſion to eat of it. ſo that this meat was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſanctifie ſinners, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it was forbidden them.</p>
                  <p>For either a ſacrifice was made for the ſins of any one who was not of the order of the Prieſts. And in this caſe one part of the ſacrifice was burnt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Altar, and the other the Prieſts did eat. For the Law gave them a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the offering which they preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for other men. <hi>Lev.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 22. and <hi>Lev.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 26. 29. <hi>Lev.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 1. &amp;c. But the ſinner, for whom the ſacrifice was made, did not taſte of it at all. Or it was done to expiate the ſins of the Prieſt himſelf, who offered for his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169751:26"/>
own tranſgreſſions. And then neither he, nor any elſe might eat of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, but it was to be wholy conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the fire. <hi>Lev.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or it was ſacrificed for the whole Body of the Church: either <hi>annually</hi> for the univerſal expiation of ſins, which was done in the name of the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; or <hi>ordinarily</hi> at ſome nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meetting, which required a general ſacrifice for the ſins of all the people. And in ſuch a caſe ſomtimes the Prieſts did eat the ſacrifice which was offred in common for the ſins of the Nation; <hi>Lev.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 17. but none of the Iſraelites, for whom this ſacrifice was made, had permiſſion to eat thereof. Moſt times, &amp; ordinarily ſuch offerings paſſed wholy through the fire, to be there conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; ſo that no body eat of it. <hi>Lev.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 13. and <hi>Lev.</hi> 16.</p>
                  <p>For the better underſtanding of all theſe diverſities, we muſt remember that there were two ſorts of Sacrifices for ſin. The One, whoſe blood was carried within the Tabernacle: The
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169751:26"/>
Other, whoſe blood was not admitted the holy place. As for the firſt, it was a general Rule, that none ſhould eat of it. For there was a Law which did expreſly forbid the eating of that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice whoſe blood was carried into the Tabernacle for the expiation of ſins. <hi>Lev.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 30. This firſt kinde of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice is mentioned by the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews, chap.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 10. As for the Other, whoſe blood came not into the holy place, they burned one part of it, and the reſt was for the eating of the Prieſts, For this cauſe the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for whom the expiatory ſacrifice was offered, had never the power to eat any portion thereof.</p>
                  <p>Whereupon we are to obſerve one very conſiderable diſtinction in the Old Teſtament. There were other ſignes repreſenting the Body of Chriſt, of which the eating was permitted to the people of the Jewes. They eat <hi>Manna,</hi> which was (in Figure) the Body of Chriſt; and drank of the Rock, which was Chriſt. They eat
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169751:27"/>
the Paſſover, which was Chriſt. They eat the Euchariſtick ſacrifices, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Jeſus Chriſt was figured. But as for the Expiatory ſacrifice, which alſo repreſents Chriſt, it was unlawful for them to eat of it. Now we muſt know that all theſe Sacrifices and Sacraments did not repreſent Jeſus Chriſt in the ſame reſpect, but every one of them had its different and particular ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; one repreſenting him in one quality, and another in another, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diverſity of his Offices and Benefits. As one and the ſame King may have divers ſeals, all bearing his image, but under divers habits, and in different poſtures. The ancient peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple then had power to communicate of all theſe Sacraments and Sacrifices, in ſome reſpect, as they ſhould repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Chriſt, except onely in that which repreſented him in as much as an Expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atory Sacrifice, which is the quality wherein he is given to us in the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt.</p>
                  <p>It is alſo to be noted, that among the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169751:27"/>
Oblations which were repreſented for ſins, there was one of Bread and Wine, which are the ſame Elements which we have in the Euchariſt, <hi>Num.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 24. This Bread, and this Wine were alſo Symboles of the Body and Blood of Chriſt. Now as for the Bread, the Law divided it between the Prieſt and the Altar, reſerving nothing for the ſinners, for whom by name it was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. The Wine alſo was forbid them: for it was all poured forth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Offering and ſerved for nothing but to ſprinckle upon it. But, at this day the Bread and Wine, Symboles of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, are exhibited to them for whom Jeſus Chriſt offered himſelf in an Expiatory Sacrifice.</p>
                  <p>From all theſe Statutes which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the formes and ſolemnities of Expiations, it appears; that the Law permits not men to eat that which is offered for the remiſſion of their ſins. It is an univerſal Rule, drawn from Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaical Right.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:169751:28"/>
Here then is very conſiderable the Oppoſition which is ſeen between the maxime of the Law, and that of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. The Law ſaith, <hi>Eat not that which is offered for the remisſion of your ſins.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Eat that which is offered for the remisſion of your ſins.</hi> For our Saviour inviting ſinners to the eating of his Body, eſtabliſhes a Principle unheard of before, and which is among the Paradoxes, <hi>That man ſhould eat the Sacrifice offered for his ſins.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We ſhall ſee anon the importance of it. In the mean while I ſhall paſs to another point, which we have already a little obſetved in this here.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The third Conſideration upon the words of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE Eating of the Expiatory Sacrifice is mentioned, as an act
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169751:28"/>
of great dignity. But it was the Prieſts Prerogative. For the Law gave the Sacrifice to be eaten, not to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for whom it was offered, but to the Prieſts which had offered it for the ſins of other men. It was the Prieſt, not the ſinner, who had charge to eat of it. <hi>Lev.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 26. and <hi>chap.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>The Prieſt who offereth the ſin Offering ſhall eat it.</hi> It belongs to the Prieſt who ſhall make propitiation by it. And it was not lawful for any of the people, although the Sacrifice were offered for them, to touch it, or come neer it, or to be found in the place where it was eaten. For the Lawgiver permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not that it ſhould be eaten any where but in the Tabernacle, whether the people entred not. The Prophet <hi>Ezekiel (chap.</hi> 46. <hi>v.</hi> 20.) conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to this Law, ſpeaking of the fleſh offered for ſins, forbids the carrying it forth into the utter Court, for fear of <hi>ſanctifying the People.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the priviledge of eating the Offering for ſin was given to the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169751:29"/>
Prieſts, for <hi>to bear the iniquity of the congregation, to make an atonement for them before the Lord.</hi> Lev. 10. v. 17. As then the Prieſts alone had the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of expiating ſins; ſo alſo to them alone did belong the eating of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering.</p>
                  <p>Hence follows. Firſt, That the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it was a Prieſtly act, as well as the immolation. Secondly, That this eating made a part of the Expiation it ſelf, or at leaſt was required to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of it. The Sinner and the Prieſt who reconciles the Sinner, are perſons much different, and their actions of a very diverſe nature. In the Old Teſtament then, the Prieſt eats that which was offered for the ſin of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. But Jeſus Chriſt hath chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged this Ordinance: For, by an Order quite new, and unheard of before, he enjoyns even Sinners themſelves to eat the fleſh offered for their ſins. So this Right which was onely the Prieſts, is now tranſported to Sinners themſelves. And whereas the Prieſt eat it, for to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169751:29"/>
the expiation of ſins; now we eat it becauſe the expiation is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy made and accompliſhed. This difference is very notable.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>That the precedent conſiderations cannot be accuſed of Nullity, whithout doing injury to the wiſdom of the Son of God.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>NOW if any man will affirm that Jeſus Chriſt thought not of all that is above ſaid, or doubt whether theſe antitheſes be the end of his words, inſtituting this Sacrament, let him again conſider, if they be not there formerly declared? If the blood of the New Covenant, which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to drink, be not manifeſtly oppoſite to that of the Old, whereof none eat? If the reaſon wherefore we are enjoyned to drink the one, be not the ſame for which it was forbidden to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169751:30"/>
taſt the other? If Jeſus Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Sinners to eat the body offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for their tranſgreſſions, thought not of the Law which forbids them to eat the fleſh ſacrificed for their ſins? If he were ignorant that it was an action of the Prieſts wherein Sinners had no part? If he knew not that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of bread and and wine, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting his Body and Blood, in as much as they were to be offered for Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, was abſolutely forbidden them? And finally; If he, who knew this Law perfectly, and repreſented his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Blood by the ſame Elements which the Law imployed to this effect, (which is ſet down in the proper termes of it, to expreſs actions unknown un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it,) hath not ſeen the conſequence thereof, nor perceived that it introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced quite new principles apparently contrary to thoſe of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nor would obſerve a difference ſo viſible, when he ſpoke even to men that were Jews, and to all future ages, who might eaſily take notice of this Noveltie?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:169751:30"/>
Certainly, foraſmuch as he layeth down maximes altogether new, which may ſeem ſtrange unto them, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſeth them that he makes a New Covenant, which aboliſheth the firſt; which contains new Clauſes, which giveth new Rights; which takes away the conditions held by the precedent, and impoſeth others altogether diſtinct from them. And as the changing of the Sacrificing hath ſhewed that there ſhould be a change of the Law; ſo the draught of the Covenant being chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, we ought not to wonder that we ſee new articles, and new orders, which anſwer not to the form and tenor of the firſt Covenant.</p>
                  <p>It is no more to be doubted, that ſuch is the ſenſe and the end of the words of Jeſus Chriſt in the Euchariſt, and thoſe who ſee it not therein, do but half underſtand it. Now the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations here above produced may it furniſh us for what follows.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:169751:31"/>
                  <head>CHAP. V. <hi>The Freface to the fourth Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Treat not here of Controverſie, nor touch the famous Diſpute of the manner of eating the Fleſh of Chriſt. Every one can ſay, that the Holy Ghoſt often ſpeaks by a Figure, and hides a Spiritual ſenſe under the name of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral things: whereupon nevertheleſs is to be obſerved, as we go, that many put Figures into thoſe words, whoſe propriety may ſubſiſt, even in a moſt excellent ſenſe. The 146. <hi>Pſalm</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth that God openeth the eyes of the blinde, and maketh ſtrait thoſe that are crooked. Some ſay that he onely ſpeakes of the illumination of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and of the health of the Soul. This is the common place, and the wide gate through which they ſhift, who finde themſelves brought to a ſtrait in any difficult paſſage: For not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169751:31"/>
being able to get out otherwiſe, they caſt themſelves on a very eaſie way, ſaying, That all this ought to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood ſpiritually. All this while they eclipſe the true light of divers paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, which have no need to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by a figure. Such a one is that which I have produced, which toucheth two excellent miracles, which were reſerved to the Son of God, in token of his Divinity. For before him never did any give ſight to the blinde, nor make ſtrait the bodies which were crooked. Wonders which his Omnipotency hath really accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, <hi>John</hi> 9. <hi>Luke</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 11, 12.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, we examine not whence it comes that Jeſus Chriſt ſpeaks ſo often by ſimilitudes; whether becauſe thoſe of the Eaſt were accuſtomed of old to propound their Doctrins under ſuch repreſentations, as we may ſee in many places of the Old Teſtament: Or, becauſe the Divine Oracles, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in what ſtyle the Meſſias would expreſs himſelf to men, had foretold
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169751:32"/>
that he would open his mouth in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. Or, becauſe he would render himſelf obſcure to unbeleevers, enve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopping his myſteries, and covering them wlth names eſtranged from the ſubject. Or, becauſe heavenly things, not having name in the language of the children of men, to whom they are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally unknown, it was needful, for to make them underſtood unto them, to ſpeak to them in their own terms: Or, becauſe that ſupernatural objects do more eaſily inſinuate into the minde, and there form more lively impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, being produced under the image of thoſe which are more perceptible to the ſenſes, then being nakedly purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in titles more thin and ſubtil. As for this phraſe which is now in agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there is none but can ſay after St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> touching the eating of the Body of Chriſt; That thoſe words, which ſeem to command a wickedneſs, ought to be taken in a figure. But this is not our queſtion here.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:169751:32"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>The fourth Conſideration upon the words of Jeſus Chriſt in the Supper.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SOME will demand why Jeſus Chriſt would ſpeak in ſuch a figure, employing a ſpeech which ſeems to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note a wickedneſs. Why is an act ſo holy, ſo noble, expreſſed by the name of an act the moſt barbarous, and the moſt unnatural that can be? For what is there more holy then the action of the Soul which unites it ſelf to Jeſus Chriſt? And what is there more abominable then to eat the fleſh of a man, and even to drink his very blood? Moreover, how can a cruelty repreſent ſo amiable a Communion? And further, from whence comes it that our Saviour recommended this Communion, would give us a deſire to it by the expreſſing of an act which breeds horrour? It ſufficeth not to ſay that it is a compariſon. It will be
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169751:33"/>
wondred at, why Jeſus Chriſt expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelf by ſo ſtrange a compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſith, that he might explain him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in other termes.</p>
                  <p>None ought to take it ill, that I handle ſuch a queſtion. There is no man having common ſenſe, into whoſe thoughts it doth not preſently enter. Moreover, we muſt know how to give an anſwer to Jewes and Atheiſts, who judge that theſe words of the Son of God are unworthy even of the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of men.</p>
                  <p>Every lawful Similitude or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon is founded on the analogy or correſpondency which is found be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two ſubjects, or elſe in ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of the one to the other. So (to give ſome examples of it, and in like termes) <hi>David,</hi> refuſing to drink the water that ſome of his people had brought him in the peril of their lives, ſaid, that it was as much as if he ſhould drink the blood of theſe men. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. <hi>v.</hi> 17. So ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſh, (Pſal.</hi> 14.) <hi>They eat my people as it were bread.</hi>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:169751:33"/>
Expreſſing a barbarous act, (to wit, the tyrannical exactions) by anothers barbariſm, which is to eat men. But to repreſent an act of Piety under the name of a prodigious Crime, this is (ſome profane ignorant perſon wil ſay) to repreſent a fair face under the ſhape of a Monſter.</p>
                  <p>It is a weak anſwer to ſay, that Jeſus Chriſt did ſpeak ſo occaſionally, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he gave them to eat: For it will alwaies be demanded, why he would repreſent the Communion of his Body by the act of eating, giving Bread to this purpoſe. Certainly, the wiſdom of God, which might have uſed to theſe ends any other ſign then nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and other expreſſions, which might ſeem more convenient, hath not uſed this here without ſome moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant reaſon, whereof I ſhall ſpeak hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:169751:34"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>The Concluſion of the Precedent Conſiderations.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WEE finde then that the Son of God repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting this ſacred and moſt bleſſed Communion, hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it with the name of two acts, the one whereof is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Ceremonial Law,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the <hi>Law Natural.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The one that we eat the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Sacrificed for our ſins, <hi>againſt all the maximes of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> The other, that we eat
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169751:34"/>
the <hi>Fleſh</hi> of the Son of man, yea, that we drink his Blood, againſt all the Laws of Nature and Humanity.</p>
                  <p>Now we muſt re-handle all the points which I have propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; examine them ſummarily. Each of them may be the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of many large diſcourſes. But mine intention is to run them over but ſo far as they ſerve to make known the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions neceſſary for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of this Sacrament, and of the words of the Son of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:169751:35"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>The Clearing of the firſt Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN The firſt place we have ſeen this oppoſition; The Law ſaith, <hi>This is the Blood which makes attonement for your Souls, wherefore none of you ſhall taſt thereof.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>This is the Blood which makes attonement for your Souls, wherefore ye ſhall all drink of it.</hi> From one and the ſame reaſon proceed two quite contrary concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p>It is then to be known, that this point of the Law touching the prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of the eating blood, depends on the other, which runs<hi>—That none might eat of that which was offered for the remisſion of their ſins.</hi> For blood was thus offred to ſuch ends; yea, no remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169751:35"/>
was made without effuſion of blood. Now as the Lawgiver had his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for which he forbids all perſons to eat that which was offered for their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement, ſo for the ſame cauſes it was in no wiſe convenient that they ſhould eat blood; yea, for ſo much the leſs, as the blood was the moſt noble part, and as it were the ſoul of ſuch offerings, and that in it conſiſted all the force and vertue of the ſacrifice. For, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive ſinners of it entirely, and to eſtrange them yet more, the prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion extended it ſelf even unto the blood; which was not actually offered, nor employed to theſe holy uſes. As if all the blood which was in the world, had been reſerved and ſet a part until the attonement for ſins had been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed in Chriſt; <hi>For, till the Blood of Chriſt was ſhed, it was not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to eat any blood.</hi> All this then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on the general rule, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids men to eat that which was offered for their ſins:</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:169751:36"/>
But Jeſus Chriſt advertiſeth us, that he hath changed this clauſe, and that he hath inſerted another in his laſt Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, whereby ſinners are hereafter enjoyned to eat that which was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for their reconciliation. In conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of which, they ought alſo to eat his Blood, as ſhed for the ſame purpoſe. Thus, as concerning blood, the ſame cauſe, from whence came the prohibition of <hi>Moſes</hi> according to the Maximes of the Law, ſerves for the ſubject of the Commandment of Chriſt according to the principles of the New Teſtament.</p>
                  <p>But it will be ſaid, was this a point of ſo great importance to eat, or not to eat the fleſh of a ſacrifice? What is the prerogative of the one, and the diſadvantage of the other? Or what is the myſtery contained in theſe words of Jeſus Chriſt? Great every way: And this is that we ought to conſider.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:169751:36"/>
                  <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>The Clearing of the ſecond Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THIS difference is touched in part by the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews, chap.</hi> 13. when he ſaith, That <hi>we have an Altar, whereof they who ſerve in the Tabernacle have no power to eat.</hi> All this is reduced to the following obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</p>
                  <p>That the remiſſion of ſins which God granted to the Fathers of the Old Teſtament, was grounded upon the expiation, which ſhould one day be made. Now this expiation remained in ſuſpence, until that Ieſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf accompliſhed it, by the Sacrifice of his Body. Therefore is it, that the ancient Fathers were ſo careful to enquire the time when Ieſus Chriſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169751:37"/>
ſhould be offered. It is not neceſſary to ſhew at large how much their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was inferiour to ours. God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver pardoned them their ſins, but by declaring to them alwaies that payment muſt be made, and that his juſtice muſt be ſatisfied. All the aſſurances that they received of their pardon, preſuppoſed alwaies an expiation which was yet to come. This held them in perpetual feare, and made them fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently deſire that this attonement might be accompliſhed in their daies, that they might dye with this joy, that the prize of their redemption was paid, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 10, 11, 12. They then aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to this oblation of the Body of Ieſus Chriſt, and deſired he would communicate himſelf unto them in the ſame fleſh, wherein he ſhould expiate their offences. For they had truly Communion with Ieſus Chriſt, but not with Ieſus Chriſt Sacrificed for ſins, as we have him at this day.</p>
                  <p>Now the Law gave then to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169751:37"/>
that as long as it had its force, they ſhould not obtain this grace: for as the way of the holy placed was not yet open, as long as the firſt Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle was ſtanding, <hi>(Heb.</hi> 9. 8.) becauſe none of the people were ſuffered to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in; ſo the Holy Ghoſt declared that the Communion of the body of Chriſt actually ſacrificed for ſins, was a benefit which we ſhould not enjoy during the ſubſiſtance of the firſt Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, which permitted not ſinners to communicate of the fleſh ſacrificed for their ſins.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, it was an infallable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence that their attonement was not yet made, whilſt they were excluded from the Communion of the expiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sacrifice.</p>
                  <p>For why ſhould they not have been admitted unto it, if by it their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions had been already expiated? The Law then taught, that they ſhould not have the true Expiatory Sacrifice, whilſt the Communion of Oblations,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169751:38"/>
which repreſented it: remained forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. This prohibition which hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them to participate of it, was a kinde of excommunication, making a part of the Legal Oeconomy, whoſe ſeverity accompanied the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to the end they might deſire a new one. From all this it appears,</p>
                  <p>That the Communion which we have with Jeſus Chriſt is more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and entire, then that under the Old Teſtament; and the application of it more efficatious.</p>
                  <p>That we are at this day nearer to God, having communion with his Son exhibited in the fleſh.</p>
                  <p>That the certainty of the Remiſſion of ſins is now more clear and diſtinct, then before the death of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>That the Law knew it not: for it ſhewed afar of the fleſh of the propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory ſacrifice, as a moſt wholſom food, and yet all this while declared to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, who had need of this remedy, that they ſhould abſtain from it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:169751:38"/>
That they who will yet practiſe the Ceremonial Law, cannot pertake of Chriſt; ſith, by the rules of it, it is not permitted unto them to eat of that fleſh, the blood whereof was carried into the holy place, for the remiſſion of ſins, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 10.</p>
                  <p>Thus the New Teſtament eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed under better promiſes, and having more favourable clauſes, gives us this advantage above the ancient Fathers, This is the New Rite which abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates the Old Law. This is the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, by which our Lord, in the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Supper, diſtinguiſheth the two Teſtaments.</p>
                  <p>When we ask the modern Iewes, from whence it comes that their cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity hath no end, and why they are not reſtored to their perfection, after ſo long expectation; They anſwer, that they have no ſacrifice, the onely means to appeaſe Gods wrath. It is fourteen hundred yeers, as <hi>Origen</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, ſince they uſed this Language;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169751:39"/>
                     <hi>our ſins remain in us, foraſmuch as we have no Sacrifice to expiate them, for want of a Lawful place.</hi> But if they could look through the vayle which covers the face of <hi>Moſes,</hi> they ſhould finde that he himſelf refuſing to make them part of ſuch oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, would advertiſe them to aſpire both to another Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to another Sacrifice, whereof they ſhould have po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to eat. For whilſt that Sinners were put by the Table of the Expiatory Sacrifice, it was a moſt evident ſign that their Expiation was not yet made. For to lead Sinners back to Chriſt, the Law had expreſly fruſtrated them of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169751:39"/>
many benefits neceſſary to their perfection. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the propitiatory Sacrifice was one of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal point which they wanted, and a grace whoſe diſpenſation was reſerved for the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:169751:40"/>
                  <head>CHAP. X. <hi>The Clearing of the third Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the Old Teſtament the Prieſt did eat the offering which he had preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the ſin of another; whereas now Sinners themſelves, for whom it was offered, are charged to eat it. What is the ſecret of ſo great a diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</p>
                  <p>It is a principle not to be doubted, that none can Expiate the ſins of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, unleſs he charge himſelf with them, and bear the pain of them, which is death. Now none can dye for the ſin of man, but man himſelf. It was then neceſſary that the Prieſt himſelf, who was to expiate the ſins of others, ſhould ſacrifice himſelf, to the end he might dye for them. Now the Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169751:40"/>
Prieſt did not Sacrifice himſelf in this action, but a goat or a Sheep died in his ſtead. But to the end that the death of the Sacrifice ſhould be thought and ſaid to be the death of the Prieſt himſelf, the Prieſt became one with it. For eating of it and incorporating of it into himſelf, he tranſported to his proper perſon the name and the effect of the death which the Sacrifice had ſuffered. In doing this, he bare the iniquity of the people, and made propitiation for them, <hi>Lev.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 17. This eating then tended to the uniting of the Prieſt with the Offering, becauſe they were two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers individuals; whereas now the Prieſt and the Offering are but one and the ſame perſon, to wit, Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>But at this day, the attonement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made, another union is neceſſary, to wit, of Sinners with the Sacrifice; to the end that having incorporated it within themſelves, the vertue of its
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169751:41"/>
death and paſſion might be imputed to them for righteouſneſs, even as if they had ſuffered in their proper perſons. It is from hence that we are enjoyned to eat the body by which our ſins are expiated; whereas the ſinners in the time of the Law could not eat it ſo, ſith, their expiation was yet to come.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>An entrance to the Clearing of the fourth Conſideration.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>NOw I muſt ſhew the reaſon of this Phraſe which ſeems to ſound ſo ill in mens ears. For to feed on the fleſh and on the blood of a man, is an action whoſe name alone brings horror; and thus as it ſeems, improper to repreſent this ſacred Communion of the body of Chriſt. Behold then what we ought to conſider. It is true that the Holy
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169751:41"/>
Ghoſt, to make himſelf underſtood, moſt times ſpeaks in termes conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the rules which common ſenſe and natural prudence hath been accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to obſerve. For beſides the propriety of tongues, wherein he hath bin pleaſed to expreſs himſelf, there are certain univerſal Laws which reaſon dictates unto men, and regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth their expreſſions; and the wiſdom of God would conform his thereunto. From thence it comes, that to expound the Scripture, we take our meaſures From arts which ſhew the congruity of language, the accord of figures, the nerves and ſinews of diſcourſe. But ſometimes the ſpirit of God hath ſpeeches and purpoſes altoghether entire, whoſe form anſwers not to ordinary rules.</p>
                  <p>Thus the holy Bible begins with theſe words, that the <hi>Elohim</hi> (which are the Perſons of the moſt bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity) created the Heaven and the Earth. Tearms whoſe conſtruction is not Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical; but which expreſs as excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169751:42"/>
as briefly, the unity of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence in the Plurality of perſons. Such a Soleciſm ſurpaſſeth all Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance.</p>
                  <p>So among many diſcourſes which Jeſus Chriſt hath uttered, there are found ſuch whoſe parts ſeem to be ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged without order; it being as it were impoſſible to ſee what agreement there is of one with the other in the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame purpoſe, and to finde their joyntings and connexions. They who Analiſe ſuch paſſages ſimply ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Logick, give them a conſtrained, and often a ridiculous ſenſe. This ſtile hath tranſcendant pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives, which we ought to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that we may know the method of the Son of God, which otherwiſe will ſeem irregular.</p>
                  <p>There you finde alſo ſimilitudes which at the firſt ſight ſeem rude and monſtrous; as when the coming of the Lord is compared to that of a thief in the night, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. and in other places. In ſuch compariſons we
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169751:42"/>
are wont to ſay, that a compariſon ſhould never be preſſed to the utmoſt; For to things alike in one regard are unlike in another. But this caution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone will not content the minde. For there hath been alwaies, whereat to wonder, that two ſubjects ſhould be compared and put together, and the one inveſted with the name of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, between which indeed there is ſome conformity, yet on the other part there ſhould be ſo great and ſo viſible a repugnance of qualities, that it renders the compariſon enormous. In this then there is a ſecret, which is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies perceivable. In the language of God, the more a phraſe is eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from our rules, the more it is my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious. That whereof the queſtion is here, is one of the moſt ſtrange in all the Scripture. But if, inſtead of be holding onely the ſuperficies, we put it in the ballance, its weight will make it known for gold of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phir.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:169751:43"/>
                  <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>The clearing of the fourth Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVHEN mention is made of <hi>Eating the Body of Chriſt,</hi> that ſpeech is not ſimply drawn from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance which there may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Eating</hi> and <hi>Communicating,</hi> and ought not to be put into the rank of ſimple ſimilitudes. This phraſe is of a higher derivation. The intention of our Saviour was to revoke a clauſe of the Old Teſtament; which was this, that a man ſhould not eat the fleſh and blood offered for the remiſſion of his ſins. We have ſeen the ſenſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of it. Jeſus Chriſt would ſhew, that he gives us that which the Law refuſed us. It was therefore ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that he ſhould expreſs it in the ſame termes; that is to ſay, that he ſhould ſpeak to us of eating the fleſh
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169751:43"/>
offered for our ſins. And that he hath done not onely in words, retaining the proper termes of the Teſtament, but alſo by the exhibition of a nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whoſe ſenſible eating is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of this other. We ought then to know, that this word of <hi>Eating,</hi> denoting the communion of the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, is not ſimply uſed, becauſe there is a reſemblance between the two acts; but foraſmuch, as in the Law this communion is called <hi>Eating.</hi> So Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt hath not introduced this word for a ſimple Metaphor or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, but hath pronounced it as a terme of a Teſtamentary clauſe, whoſe repetition was here neceſſary for the cauſe aboveſaid. For this terme being already in the firſt Teſtament to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs this Communion, muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>It Bootes not to ſay, that the name of <hi>Eating,</hi> which denotes an act of the mouth, and of the teeth upon the fleſh of Legal offerings, is not convenient to the Communion of a humane body,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169751:44"/>
as is that of Chriſts, and that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of it is rude. For to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this terme, we muſt take the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire ſenſe, which extends it ſelf a great deal farther then a ſimple compariſon. In the inſtitution of the Supper, this Communion is not ſimply qualifed, <hi>Eating of a Body given for Food,</hi> but of a body given for the attonement of our ſins. Now this ſpeech means, that the Communion of the Body of Chriſt, which we know to be ſpiritual, is in effect what the eating of expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atory Sacrifice was in figure. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, that the body of Chriſt having ſucceeded Sacrifices, the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Body hath taken the place of eating (of) Sacrifices. This title then belongs to it, not by ſimple re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, but (if I may ſo ſay) both by ſucceſſion, and in the ſame ſort that Jeſus Chriſt is called Paſſover and Lamb; the truth taking the name of the Figure. As for the words of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, in the ſixth Capter of Saint <hi>John,</hi> although they have reference
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169751:44"/>
to thoſe of the Holy Supper, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs their interpretation requires particular conſiderations, which I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, foraſmuch as I treat of nothing here but what our Saviour ſaid in the Euchariſt. Nevertheleſs we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve as we goe, that the Communion of the body of Chriſt, is there called Eating, not by a ſimple ſimilitude, but is as much as to ſay, that this Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is in effect, and in ſubſtance, that which the eating of the <hi>Manna</hi> was in ſhadow and ſimilitude. For the Jews had objected this eating of the <hi>Manna.</hi> Finally, for to meaſure this phraſe in all its dimenſions, it is not enough there to conſider the analogy between the <hi>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> with the mouth and the <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating</hi> in ſpirit. For this reſemblance is not the onely cauſe of this expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor the onely point we ought to draw to in concluſion.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, our Lord would ſhew that a ſpiritual life hath principles much different from a life animal. Both have this common to them, that their
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169751:45"/>
ſubſiſtance depends on the union of man with ſome other ſubject, which we call aliment: But in the life natural man hath no proper aliments, which are not of a kinde inferiour to his own. ſuch are plants and their fruits, ſuch is the fleſh of bruit beaſts, which we lodg in our intrales, mingling their blood with ours, and uniting th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m to our own ſubſtance. Man is conſtrained to incorporate into himſelf theſe vile things, and which are much below him. On the contrary, in a ſpiritual life he unites himſelf to a ſubject infinitely more excellent then himſelf, to wit, to the Eternal Spirit; for it is the Spirit which quickens. Now this Spirit Communicates himſelf unto us in the Fleſh of Chriſt. So that his Fleſh is unto us Meat indeed. In which is ſeen this diverſity; That in the Life Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, man and his food ought to be of different kindes: But in the Life Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, man and his food ought to be of one and the ſame kinde.</p>
                  <p>Therefore it is that our Saviour
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169751:45"/>
expreſſeth the Communion of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by the name of this act, contrary to Nature, (which is to eat the fleſh of man) for to ſignifie, that a Spiritual Life is maintained by a means quite contrary to that which Nature em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploys in an Animal Life. For to <hi>Eat the fleſh of the Son of man,</hi> ſignifies not onely <hi>to have Communicated with him,</hi> but ſignifies alſo, <hi>that this Communion is not according to the Laws of Nature.</hi> And the words of the Son of God bear not onely a ſimilitude of qualities, but alſo note an oppoſition of kinde between the food of the Body and the nouriſhment of the Spirit. All this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boveſaid being duely conſidered, we ſhall finde that this phraſe which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo ſtrange could not be more preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, more compleat, nor more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venicent for the ſubject.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:169751:46"/>
                  <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>The fift Conſideration upon the words of Jeſus Chriſt in the Supper.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SINCE Jeſus Chriſt ſpeaks of a Teſtament whoſe laſt ſeal is the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, a Chriſtian ought to learn what this Teſtament is, for to know the importance of the ſeal which we ſee put to it: and principally it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to have regard to that which Jeſus Chriſt ſaid thereof when he inſtituted the Supper. For he advertiſeth us that this Teſtament is New; that is to ſay, ſucceeds another, which is aboliſhed by this latter. Moreover, that this Teſtament is <hi>with the Blood of the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor;</hi> that is to ſay, that he died in this laſt <hi>Will.</hi> Now I omit to ſhew, why he would make a ſecond Teſtament, and if there wanted any thing in the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169751:46"/>
firſt, it will ſuffice to obſerve thence, that the firſt Teſtament was of no force in compariſon of the ſecond. For a Teſtament hath no vertue during the life of the Teſtator; nor can it ſend forth its effect, unleſs the death of the Teſtator intervene, <hi>Hebrews</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 16, 17. So that the Old Teſtament had no force in its time, becauſe that Jeſus Chriſt was not yet dead. But the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament which we have at this day hath been made efficatious by the death of the Teſtator.</p>
                  <p>Some Jew, who cannot perſwade him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that God would aboliſh the firſt Covenant by a ſecond, that which nevertheleſs he ought to have learned of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 31. <hi>v.</hi> 31, &amp;c. will tell us that this will make us doubt, whether or no there ſhall be yet a third. But this is no reaſon; For the Covenant of God was conceived in form of a Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or of a donation by reaſon of Death. Now the Teſtator being once dead, there is no place for another Teſtament. The laſt Will where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169751:47"/>
he died, remaines irrevocable for ever.</p>
                  <p>Finally, there is this thing extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary; that death permitting none to be executor of his own Teſtament, Jeſus Chriſt contrarily is come from death to life for to execute his; foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as none was capable of this charge; For he is riſen again for our ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 25.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:169751:47"/>
                  <head>CHAP. XIIII. <hi>The ſixth Conſideration upon the words of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>MY <hi>Blood,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is ſhed for the remisſion of ſins.</hi> We know that his death ought to be bloody, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Maxime,</hi> which ſays, <hi>that there is no remisſion of ſins made without effuſion of blood,</hi> Hebrewes 9. Now we demand not here, why this remiſſion could not be obtained other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that is to ſay, why it behoved that the death of our Saviour, ſhould not onely be violent, but alſo be mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked with blood. Nevertheleſs, that which I have to obſerve thereupon, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be conſidered. Death, which is the wages of ſin, began by effuſion of blood. The firſt that ever died, (which was <hi>Abel)</hi> died of a bloody death. As then the blood of man hath been
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169751:48"/>
the firſt fruits of death, ſo alſo was it the concluſion and deſtruction of it. Death began by blood, and ended by blood.</p>
                  <p>Between this firſt blood which was ſhed upon the Earth, and the Blood of the Son of God, there is a very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable oppoſition, touched by the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> Chapter 12. to wit, that the Blood of <hi>Sprinkling,</hi> which is that of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>ſpeaks better things, then that of</hi> Abel: For this cried out for the the puniſhment of ſin; but the other cries for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins.</p>
                  <p>It is alſo obſervable, that the ſame man who died firſt of all, is alſo the firſt (in the holy Hiſtory) who had ſacrificed with blood. For he was the firſt that offered the fleſh and fat of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Creatures, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 4. 4. So the firſt who felt death brought forth by ſin, is alſo the firſt, who offered the bloody Oblation whereby we ſhould be delivered from ſin, which is the ſting of death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:169751:48"/>
Finally, The Jews, who think it ſtrange that the Blood of a Man is our Expiation, have nevertheleſs an ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, which cannot ſubſiſt but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this principle, That there muſt be an humane Sacrifice to wipe away the ſins of man.</p>
                  <p>They beleeve that God will give them grace, in contemplation of the obedience of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> who expoſed himſelf voluntarily to be ſacrificed. And they have prayers, wherein they alledge the merit of this Sacrifice, as a foundation of the Redemption which they expect. Now as for the offering of this Patriarch, if it had been capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to expiate the ſins of his Off-ſpring, even of thoſe who live at this day; why, after this Sacrifice of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſhould there be yet need of ſo many expiatory Sacrifices? To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe hath the Law, which is ſince gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, impoſed upon them Sacrifices for the obtaining of pardon? But to ſpeak no more of it, <hi>Iſaac</hi> was not ſacrificed in effect, and his blood was
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:169751:49"/>
not ſhed in this Oblation. Which ſhews that it is not expiatory. For without an actual effuſion of blood, no remiſſion of ſins at all is made. The Law tells them, that it is blood which makes expiation for the Soul. <hi>Lev.</hi> 17.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>The ſeventh Conſideration upon the words of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE Inſtitution of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is compriſed in few words, whereof not one is vain. For Jeſus Chriſt hath ſaid nothing which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains not ſome great point. Now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, he ſhewes what is the vertue and dignity of the Blood which he preſents unto us; and this in four divers reſpects; to wit,</p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:169751:49"/>
                     <item>1. That it is his own Blood, the Blood of the Son of God.</item>
                     <item>2. That it is the Blood of the New Covenant.</item>
                     <item>3. That this Blood purchaſes unto us remiſſion of ſins.</item>
                     <item>4. That this Blood is ſhed for many.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>As for this laſt, amongſt many other matters therein contained, I think that our Lord would yet touch upon a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference alſo between the Blood of the Old Teſtament, and that of the New.</p>
                  <p>In the Old Teſtament, the Blood of the Sacrifice was ſometimes em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed only for the expiation of one man among the people, who had need of a particular ſacrifice. Now this Sacrifice which was offred but for one man alone, was many wayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to that which was offred for many, that is to ſay, for the Multitude, or for all the Church. Principally in this, that the Blood ſhed in Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for one man alone, never came into the Holy Place; But that did,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169751:50"/>
which was ſhed for the multitude. Jeſus Chriſt therefore advertiſeth us, that his Blood was ſhed for many, for the Multitude, to the end that we might know that his Blood hath pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrated the Holy Places, and hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened them, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 12. And in this alſo is the New Teſtament more excellent than the Old. For the Blood of the Old Teſtament did not alwayes enter within the Holy Place.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, the Blood of the Old Teſtament, which was ſhed for one man alone, was not ſufficient even to Expiate (legally) all the ſins of ſuch a man, but onely a particular offence, for which by name there wholly nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a Sacrifice. On the contrary, the Blood of the New Teſtament, was not onely ſhed for many men, but hath alſo Expiated univerſally all the ſins of every one of them. So that if one of my ſins hath been Expiated in this Blood, all my other ſins have there their Expiation alſo, for it is generall and entire.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:169751:50"/>
So then the termes of the Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if wee know how to weigh them, cauſe us to know that Jeſus Chriſt hath ſounded all the profundities of the Old Teſtament, and drawes from thence thoſe points which ſhew the excellency and advantages of the New, by comparing them together.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>The eighth Conſideration upon the words of the holy Supper.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Intend not to reiterate that which hath been ſo much written; how the Bread is the Body of Chriſt; but onely to obſerve ſomething upon a queſtion which is common enough, <hi>viz.</hi> Why our Lord did not ordain Fleſh, rather than Bread, for to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his Body. For it ſeems that this Symbole ſhould be more analogick and ſignificative. According to the ſaying of many, it is foraſmuch as
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169751:51"/>
Fleſh hath ſerved in old time in the Sacrifices, and in the Paſſeover; and that it behoves that the Sacraments of the Chriſtian Church ſhould be of other Elements than thoſe that have ſerved under the Law.</p>
                  <p>But this anſwer is ill grounded, for 1. The Bread and Wine were alſo uſed in Sacrifices. There was by name an Oblation of Bread and Wine, <hi>Numb.</hi> 15. not to ſpeak of the Shew-bread, and of the Offerings of Cakes. 2. The Element of Water ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for Legall purifications: Under the Law there was nothing ſo ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as the waſhing with Water, to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the clenſing of the Soul. Yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe God would that Baptiſm ſhould be with Water. 3. The contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is rather true, and this is that alſo which ſome ancient Fathers ſay of it, That in this action Jeſus Chriſt uſeth Bread and Wine, becauſe that theſe Elements had already been uſed under the Law to repreſent his Body and his Blood. And this, to the end we ſhould
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:169751:51"/>
know, that it is the ſame Chriſt repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the ſame ſignes.</p>
                  <p>But why then hath not the Fleſh of living Creatures as well place in the Sacrament of the Euchariſt, ſith it hath repreſented Chriſt in that of the Paſſeover, and in ſo many kinds of Sacrifices? We ſay indeed that Chriſt hath rather choſen Bread, becauſe it is the moſt common, and the moſt nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing food, and ſo moſt proper to repreſent his Body. But this excludes not other reaſons which we may give thereof. Moreover, the Euchariſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents not the Body of Jeſus Chriſt ſimply, as <hi>nouriſhment,</hi> but alſo as <hi>dead.</hi> Now ſome may ſay, (which nevertheleſſe is not without contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,) that the Death of Chriſt was in Old time more ocularly repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the killing of a Lamb, than at this day by the breaking of Bread. So it is, this is the point I am to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, that Jeſus Chriſt inſtituting ſigns of his Dead Body, and of his Blood ſhed, did chooſe things without life,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169751:52"/>
and Elements wherein there was no Blood. Whereby he would ſhew, that after him no creature ſhould any more loſe his life for the ſins of man, and that no other Blood ſhould be ſhed in Expiation. For the Sacraments of the Old Teſtament were Bloody, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note the Blood which was to be ſhed by the death of Chriſt. But, this effuſion being made, the Sacraments which repreſent it as done and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, are without effuſion of Blood, to ſhew that there ſhall be no more Blood ſhed for ſins. Hence it is wee have no more a Sacrament which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the killing of any creature, but Signes, wherein death doth not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene, as being of themſelves without life, and of another ſubſtance than of Fleſh and Blood.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:169751:52"/>
                  <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>The ninth Conſideration upon the words of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>MEn, principally the common people, do naturally love Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes, becauſe they are drawn from things perceptible to the ſenſes, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe common and eaſie to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. But ſimilitudes repreſent not the eſſence of a ſubject, and doe not ſay what a thing is, but what it reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. So our Lord would not tell us ſimply, that his Body had reſemblance unto Bread, nor onely that the Bread is a Seal unto us of the Communion of his Body, but alſo hath ſhewed us the cauſes and qualities of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. Theſe words, <hi>To eat the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſignifie not onely <hi>to take it for the Suſtenance of our Souls, as we take food for the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Bodyes.</hi> This Similitude, if we ſpecifie no more, teacheth us but
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169751:53"/>
very generally the nature of this Communion, and doth not ſet forth the entire ſenſe of the words of Jeſus Chriſt. For in the Euchariſt our Lord doth not propound himſelf as <hi>Fleſh</hi> in generall, but as <hi>Fleſh ſacrifiſed for our ſins,</hi> which is a point of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence in this matter.</p>
                  <p>I have already ſaid that the word <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> is attributed to the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the body of Chriſt, which is as much as to ſay, that this Communion is in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance that which was in Figure the eating of Sacrifices, of the Manna, of the Paſſeover, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And namely, that in this Communion we have that which the Law forbad us, to wit, the eating of the Fleſh offred for our ſins. They, who content themſelves with the generall ſimilitudes between the Food of the Body, and the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Soul, attain not unto the ſpecifick difference of the ſubject of the Euchariſt. But I have yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to ſay of an abuſe which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the deduction of this Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169751:53"/>
For as many omit that which is contained in the words of the holy Supper, ſo there are ſome (I ſpeak even of Orthodox Divines) who adde thereto ſomething of their own.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>The tenth Conſideration upon the words of Jeſus Chriſt in the Supper.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WEe know that wee ought not to carry a Similitude beyond its end. For when two divers things are compared to one another, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in all, and through all, but onely in ſome regard. When (for example) our Lord in St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 46. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares the kingdome of Heaven to a Pearl of great price, his intention is but to expreſs the greatneſs of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue and richneſs of the Goſpell. Now he that would, under pretence of this word <hi>Pearl,</hi> diſpute philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phically of all the kinds and proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169751:54"/>
of Pearls, ſearch of what matter they are made, and how they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and ſubtilly fit all this to the kingdome of Heaven would ſurpaſſe the bounds wherein Jeſus Chriſt hath confined the ſimilitude. For he doth not in all qualities compare the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven to a Pearl, but onely in the price or eſteem which men have of it. Notwithſtanding there are few found among thoſe who expound the Scriptures, who keep themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe limits. There are even of thoſe who regard no meaſure when they handle a compariſon. If our Saviour ſay that he is a Vine, they will name all ſorts of Vines, and their differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and tell you what territory is proper to them, when they are to bee planted, how they are to be pruned and kept; Alſo, what are the parts of this Plant, even unto the leaſt leaf. And likewiſe, if their text ſpeak of the Sower, they will diſplay all huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry. On a time a knowing man, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding unto us that which is ſaid of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169751:54"/>
                     <hi>the Longitude, and Latitude, depth and heigh of the love of God, Epheſ.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 18. preached unto us all the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, from a Point even unto the Squaring of a Circle; ſo that one would have thought him an interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Euclide,</hi> and not of Saint <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo many handle the doctrine of the Supper, who teach that among the Analogies by which the bread repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the body of Chriſt, this is one; That as the Bread was baked in the Oven by the heat of the fire, ſo the Body of Jeſus Chriſt paſſed through the furnace of torments, and of death. Alſo, that as the Bread is made of Wheat which was ground and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſo the Body of Jeſus Chriſt was broken to be made bread for us. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as for the other ſign; that as the Wine warms the entrailes, ſo doth the Blood of Chriſt warm our hearts to Charity. That as the Wine doth looſe the tongue, ſo the Blood of Chriſt makes us eloquent to confeſs his name. That as the Wine makes ruddy the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169751:55"/>
face of man, ſo the Blood of Chriſt drives away the paleneſs of death.</p>
                  <p>Now, ſaving the reſpect due to Predeceſſours, and not to ſpeak of that which would ſeem ridiculous in ſuch Allegories, I cannot abſtain from ſaying that they ſtretch this analogy beyond the intention of the Son of God; for firſt his death is not repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto us by the baking of Bread, but rather by the breaking of it, nor by the bruiſing of the grain under the mill-ſtone. Moreover, in the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt the Bread and Wine are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered univerſally in all their propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties and conditions. For bread and wine have alſo qualities, wherein they have no analogy with the body and blood of our Lord. And even all the qualities wherein the bread and wine have any ſimilitude with the body and blood of Chriſt, are not ſacramentall, but onely thoſe that are compriſed in the Inſtitution. That, which is Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall in them, is, that they are Meat and Drink, that we Eat the one,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169751:55"/>
and Drink the other; in which reſpect they are ſigns of our Communion of the body and blood of Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 16. The other conformities which are to be found between the body of Chriſt and the bread, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the blood of Chriſt and the wine, have no place in the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, neither are there to be conſidered. Wee ought not to multiply the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy between the ſigne inaſmuch as a ſigne, and the thing ſignified. And finally, when theſe analogies, which we there meet with, are not propoſed as Sacramentall, but onely as termes ſerving to illuſtrate or amplifie, we ſee manifeſtly that in the moſt part of them, in ſtead of fitting the Similitude to the Subject which they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent, they fit the Subject to the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, drawing it by force into the Compariſon. Now this is not to clear, but to make more intricate. And in ſuch amplifications there is more words, than ſubſtance.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:169751:56"/>
               <head>The Third Sect.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the difference between the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts reciting the Inſtitution of the Supper.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> and the three Evangeliſts who have wrote this Hiſtory, doe report ſomething diverſly the words of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. This difference may eaſily be perceived by hearing them ſpeak together. Now it is not neceſſary to repeat what the Expoſitors anſwer thereupon. The whole being well conſidered, there will alwayes be found an excellent harmony, and one and the ſame ſenſe. But, foraſmuch as the Jews object unto us this diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity as a note of diſcord among the writers of the New Teſtament, wee
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:169751:56"/>
muſt bring to their remembrance the difference which is found between <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> writing the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue in two ſeverall places, <hi>viz.</hi> in the 20. of <hi>Exodus,</hi> and the 5. of <hi>Deuteronomy.</hi> By Compariſon of both, we ſee not onely that there is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of termes, but alſo in the one there are things which are not expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the other. I omit the difference which wee ſee in the order of words conteined in the laſt Commandment. We muſt obſerve that God doth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver repeat the ſame thing, but it is with ſome diverſity, at leaſt for the moſt part. This is ſeen by comparing the Hiſtories which treat of the ſame ſubject; as <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> with the three precedent books; the books of <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles,</hi> with thoſe of <hi>Samuel,</hi> and of the <hi>Kings;</hi> the Evangeliſts one with the other; Beſides an infinite number of paſſages which are of like ſort, wherein is alwayes obſerved ſome difference. It is an effect of the care which God hath of us, explaning
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169751:57"/>
himſelf by divers wayes, by a divers order, by divers termes, and by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers matters, to the end that thoſe things which are obſcure unto us in one place, ſhould be made intelligible unto us by another. And indeed, the ſence of Sacramentall words is better known by the diverſity wherein they are propounded unto us, than if they we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> all rendered in the ſame ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles throughout all the Evangeliſts.</p>
                  <p>Finally, it may be obſerved as wee goe, that as the Decalogue (wherein God ſpeaks unto us,) is written twice at large, in the Law; ſo the Lords Prayer, in which we ſpeak to God, is written twice at large, in the Goſpell, and alſo with ſome diverſity, <hi>viz.</hi> in St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. and St. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:169751:57"/>
                  <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the firſt and laſt Sacrament of the Eating of the body of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FRom the fall of man, even untill <hi>Moſes,</hi> there was no Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Eating, during all that time the Church had no Sacrament which conſiſted in eating, nor yet any Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice whereof it was ordained to eat. Before <hi>Moſes,</hi> they ſpake ordinarily of nothing but of Sacrifices, laid whole on the Altar, whereof none was eaten. For this kind of Sacrifice was entirely burned. The firſt Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice which was ordained for meat, was the Paſchall Lamb. The eating of Sacrifices is come up ſince, as that of <hi>Manna,</hi> which yet was extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary.</p>
                  <p>Now this is worthy to be obſerved, that in one and the ſame ſupper Jeſus Chriſt celebrated the firſt and the laſt Sacrament of the Eating of his body,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:169751:58"/>
                     <hi>viz.</hi> the Paſſeover and the Euchariſt. And from the ſame bread and wine which made part of the Supper of the Paſſeover, he hath taken the ſignes whereof is compoſed the holy Supper. So the firſt and the laſt Sacrament of the Eating of the body of Chriſt are met and touch one another at the ſame Table; and the firſt reſigning his place to the other, hath furniſhed it with matter whereof it is formed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the firſt and laſt Paſſeover mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Scripture.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ALthough the Paſſeover was ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated yearly among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, nevertheleſs holy hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry recites particularly certain memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Paſſovers amongſt others, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnized at divers times.</p>
                  <p>The firſt, when the Iſraelites prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves to go out of <hi>Egypt, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od.</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:169751:58"/>
The ſecond, in the Deſert, the year after their going out of <hi>Egypt, Numb.</hi> 9.</p>
                  <p>The third, when they were entred into the land of <hi>Canaan, Joſ.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>The fourth, at the Reformation of the Church, made by <hi>Ezekias,</hi> 2 <hi>Chronic.</hi> 30.</p>
                  <p>The fift, under King <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.</p>
                  <p>The ſixt, after the Return from the Captivity, <hi>Eſdras</hi> 6.</p>
                  <p>This is the number of thoſe which were mentioned in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, four whereof were celebrated in the Land of promiſe: But the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, which is the perfection of all the reſt, was yet to come. And it is that which Jeſus Chriſt hath celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the laſt of all, whereto immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſucceeded the Supper.</p>
                  <p>In this laſt Paſsover, the <hi>Lamb</hi> it ſelf is there found in the very Fleſh, which had been repreſented by the Lambs of former Paſsovers.</p>
                  <p>Wee muſt alſo note that Jeſus
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169751:59"/>
Chriſt, who celebrated the laſt Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, was there where the firſt was celebrated, to wit, in <hi>Egypt.</hi> Neither is it without a myſtery, that, as the Paſsover came from <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſo Jeſus Chriſt, who is the true Paſsover, was called out of <hi>Egypt. Matth.</hi> 2. 15.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>Of the time of the Inſtitution of the Supper, and that its durance ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that of the Moſaicall Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AS for the Circumſtance of time wherein the Euchariſt was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, although it be not of the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of it, nevertheleſs it is very conſiderable in that it concurrs with the time of the moſt notable Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Law. There are ſome Chronologers who think that the ſame year, wherein Chriſt was put to death, was a year of Jubilee; For
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:169751:59"/>
from the Conqueſt of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> by <hi>Joſuah,</hi> untill the death of Chriſt, they account 1400. years, which contain 28. Moſaicall Jubilees; the laſt whereof fell juſt in the year wherein our Lord made overture of the ſpirituall Jubilee, the day after the Inſtitution of the Supper. We might quote many other the like conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. The hour wherein Jeſus Chriſt gave up the Ghoſt upon the Croſs was the third in the afternoon, which the Jew accounted the ninth hour of the day. The Law names it the time between two evenings. And in that hour there was a daily Sacrifice for all the people, <hi>Exod.</hi> 29. <hi>v.</hi> 39. So that our Lord preſented his Body in Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſame hour wherein they offered according to the Law the laſt Sacrifice of the day, making it alſo the cloſe of all Sacrifices. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the Sacraments of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church have already dured longer than the Legall Ceremonies to which they ſucceeded. For it is certain that
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:169751:60"/>
from the firſt Supper untill this day, there is more time paſſed then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the firſt Paſsover, and the laſt deſtruction of the Temple. And theſe Ceremonies of <hi>Moſes</hi> have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready buried longer than they ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. But this laſt Sacrament of Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Body of Chriſt, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main till he comes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 26.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the difference of the ſtyle betwixt the Inſtitution of the Paſsover, and that of the Euchariſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WE way ſee in the 12th Chapter of <hi>Exodus,</hi> the Inſtitution of the Paſsover recited very amply, whereas that of the Euchariſt is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed in very few words. Now this difference proceeds certainly from this, that the one contains a multitude of Ceremonies, which requires many more articles, and the other conſiſts
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:169751:60"/>
in the ſimplicity of an action which may be declared in few words. Hereby alſo we ſee that the Church hath been diſcharged of many burthenſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations. The Jews having calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all the Commandements contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as well <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> as <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> and <hi>Politick,</hi> have found them to amount to the number of 613. Among which there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny which are yet ſubdivided into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers branches. Now of ſo many Commandements it is not poſſible for them at this day to obſerve ſo much as the one half of them.</p>
                  <p>But I obſerve that the Inſtitution of the Paſsover ſpeaks much more of the ſign than of the thing ſignified. For <hi>Moyſes</hi> having deſcribed at large all that concerned the Lamb and its ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, when he comes to the thing ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified he expreſſth it very ſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 26. 27. It is alſo the ſtyle of the law to be prolix in the narration of Sacrifices, of waſhings, and outward purifications, and to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:169751:61"/>
ſpeak very briefly of ſpirituall graces repreſented under ſuch figures. Now this was the Methode of the legall Pedagogy to teach men rather by Emblemes and rudiments, than by an exact doctrine, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>On the contrary, the Sacraments of the Chriſtian Church are propoſed unto us with leſſe Ceremonies and more doctrine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>That the Holy Supper conſiſts in ſignes and actions common and naturall.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Will adde a Reaſon to thoſe which are more ordinary upon this ſubject. We know that there are many points of the Ceremoniall Law, which the Jews cannot practiſe at this day; not becauſe they have no more a Temple; but becauſe they are gnorant of the form, and the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of many things which the Law
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:169751:61"/>
had preſcrib'd to their forefathers. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the examples which may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in great number, I ſhall obſerve onely one or two. The Jewes think themſelves oblig'd (by the words of the 30. of <hi>Exod. v.</hi> 13.) to pay year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for pious works, half a ſhekel for each head. Now, as they ſay, they know not what a ſhekel was, its weight, and its value. So that the practice of this Commandement, and of many others whoſe ſenſe is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, is altogether impoſſible for them. And if ſuffizes not to ſay, that they might give more than the ſhekel was worth. For this is to be alwayes ignorant of the point wherein the Law conſiſts, and whoſe obſervation. (as of all the other Ceremonies) ought to be exact and preciſe, under pain of non-acceptance. Likewiſe it is uncertain whether the Phylacteries which the Jews will yet wear accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law, were of fringe, or elſe of filleting or bordering; and of what colour the thred or twiſt was,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:169751:62"/>
whether of Purple, or of Skie-colour, or Sea-green. For they are not agreed of it. I omit the diſputes which there are concerning the Cubits and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Altar; concerning the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of the Cherubims; the ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients deſtined for the anointing of the High-Prieſt; Urim and Thum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mim, and things of like ſort.</p>
                  <p>Now we muſt know, that God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this Law, and nevertheleſſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an intention to abrogate it after a certain time, and foreſeeing alſo the ſtubbornneſs of this people, who would never quit theſe Ceremoniall Rudiments, compoſed them of matters and forms ſubject to change and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſs, to the end that of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they might be aboliſhed. For the weights and meaſures, colours, and faſhions of veſtments, of Embroyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reries and Pourtraitures, and other dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, wherein conſiſted a great part of Ceremonies, are changeable things, and which are deſtroy'd with the time, as being more of Art than of Nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:169751:62"/>
But on the contrary our Saviour willing to Inſtitute Sacraments which ſhould remain to the end of the world, made them of matters and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, which never change nor vary, as being naturall, ſimple, uniform, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall, and common to all ages: Such is the waſhing with water, ſuch is eating and drinking. Foraſmuch as they are actions invariable and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, Jeſus Chriſt hath choſen them for Signes, to the end that our Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhould not be ſubject to change, and that the time might not make us forget a form.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>That our Saviour hath not prefixed any time for the Celebration of the Supper.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe Paſsover could not be Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated but at a ſet time of the year. But Jeſus Chriſt ſubſtituting the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:169751:63"/>
Supper to the Paſsover, advertiſeth us, that without diſtinction of time, as often as we ſhall take this Bread and this Cup in remembrance of him, we ſhall receive the Supper of the Lord. It is to be noted, that the difference of <hi>Times,</hi> of <hi>Places,</hi> and of <hi>Perſons,</hi> to which God hath reſtrained the moſt notable Ceremonies of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, tended to the end which we have named; to wit, to facilitate their abrogation. For he tyed the Sacrifices to one place alone; whoſe poſſeſſion comming to deſtruction, all the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices ought to ceaſe. And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently bound the Prieſtly office to one family alone; which comming to be extinguiſh'd of it ſelf, (as races are deſtroyed in time) there ought to be no more a Prieſt. The which is alſo come to paſſe. For if at this day the the Jewes ſhould recover, and build again the Temple, they would find no Prieſt according to the Law<hi>:</hi> foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as their Tribes having been confounded, there is none left who
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:169751:63"/>
can term himſelf of the family of <hi>Aaron.</hi> Touching the diſtinction of times (without ſpeaking of Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which have ſince happened by the ignorance of the courſe of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and of the continuall retrogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Equinox) the Jewes have loſt the knowledge of the year of Jubilee one of the great points of the Law, and know not how any more to find it.</p>
                  <p>But the Sacraments of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church were not ſubject to this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience, nor to divers others which followed the Moſaicall Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. Our Baptiſm is not fixed to the eighth day, nor our Lords Supper to the full Moon, or to the Spring time, or unto the Sabbath it ſelf. If ſome Chriſtians ſhould be under thoſe Climats where one day dures many moneths, and the night as long, they would there have no week nor Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day: and nevertheleſs might ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate the Supper of the Lord, and his reſurrection as well as wee upon Eaſter day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:169751:64"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Why Jeſus Chriſt is repreſented unto us in the Supper as he was on the Croſs, and not as he is in heaven; alſo why hee hath not Inſtituted a Sacrament which ſhould repreſent him in his glory, as he hath ordained two, which repreſent him dead.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ALL the Sacraments ſpeak of <hi>Death.</hi> As for Baptiſm it is ſaid, <hi>that wee are baptized in the death of Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 6. <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4. As for the Supper, <hi>Wee ſhew thereby the Lords death,</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 26. And both were Inſtituted when Jeſus Chriſt was yet mortall. For no Sacrament was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Jeſus Chriſt glorified; but onely he confirmed thoſe which he had Inſtituted before his death.</p>
                  <p>Wee know then that in the Supper Jeſus Chriſt is exhibited unto us as dead, and not as glorified. Now this ſerves to ſhew the falſity of the corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reall
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:169751:64"/>
preſence for which there is ſo much diſpute. For if the body of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt be in the Hoſt, he is not there living, ſith that he is in this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as dead. It makes us alſo ſee the nakedneſs of that which is called Concomitance, and of the unbloody Sacrifice. For the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt is preſented unto us as ſeparate from his body. This likewiſe makes unprofitable the exception whereby it is maintained that a glorious body may be corporally in divers places at one and the ſame time. For were it ſo, the body of Jeſus Chriſt is not exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto us as glorious, nor yet as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; but as dead, as broken; and his blood as ſhed. Let this be ſaid by the way; For Orthodox divines have made theſe reaſons of force enough.</p>
                  <p>But it may be demanded why Jeſus Chriſt is repreſented unto us as dead, and not glorified? Is it there ſpoken of his Death, and not rather of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection? Why had he rather Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute a memoriall of his ignomious
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:169751:65"/>
humiliation, than of his glorious exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation? Why have we no Sacrament which repreſents unto us his body glorious, as we have two which repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him dead? For it is very true, that the conſideration of his humiliation excludes not that of his exaltation; on the contrary, it leads us to it: But pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and formally the Body of Jeſus Chriſt is not repreſented, nor conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Supper but as dead &amp; broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>This queſtion is eaſie to be reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. The Sacraments are Inſtituted in favour of men. And the end of a Sacrament is to aſſure us of our good and ſalvation. So in the Supper, the intention of Jeſus Chriſt was thereby to ſeal and ratifie that which concerns us, not that which concerns himſelf. And for this reaſon he preſents him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in this action inaſmuch as he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the glory of others, not ſo much as he poſſeſſeth his own. Now it is by his death, that he hath procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our glory. True it is that his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation is alſo our Salvation; But he
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:169751:65"/>
hath received this Glory both for us and for himſelf, whereas his Death was wholly for us. Moreover it is by vertue of his Death, that his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification is profitable unto us. For that he hath taken poſſeſſion of the heavens in our name, and that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercedes for us at the right hand of God, all this comes from the merit of his Blood, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. v. 12. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more Jeſus Chriſt doth give him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unto us in the Euchariſt inaſmuch as he was delivered up for us, <hi>Luke</hi> 22<hi>: v</hi> 19, 20: Now it was in his Death that he was delivered; So that he gives himſelf unto us as Dead. Finally he would leave us a remembrance of the love which he bare us. Now the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt effect wherein this love appeared, was that he gave himſelf to Death for us. It is for this cauſe, that he repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents unto us rather his Death, than his Exaltation. From thence it is that in the Supper, although wee ought to lift our hearts up to heaven where
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:169751:66"/>
he is now living in full Majeſty, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs his body broken and his blood ſhed are the proper and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall object of our contemplation. And the act of our mind conſiſts in this, that we there conſider his Death paſt, rather than his preſent Glory. This will furniſh an anſwer for the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing queſtion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Why in the Supper Jeſus Chriſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted not more illuſtrious Signes; and why they are not miraculous.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THere is none of us who hath not this thought, when he ſees that this Sacrament, as well as Baptiſm, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in ſuch abject matters; Our eye is aſtoniſh't to ſee nothing more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. The Bow in the heaven which God made <hi>Noah</hi> to ſee for aſſurance that from thence-forth there ſhould
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:169751:66"/>
no more an univerſall deluge ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; The Pillar of fire, and the Cloud which witneſſed the preſence of God among the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> The going back of the Sun to confirm the faith of <hi>Ezekias;</hi> had a more famous appearance than our Sacraments. Wee will ſay, as it is true, that the elements whereof they are compoſed, are more important to man. For the uſe of water, eating and drinking are more neceſſary for us, than the ſight of more majeſticall objects. Now it is that God would repreſent unto us benefits neceſſary for the ſoul, under the image of thoſe which are moſt neceſſary for the body. I omit the other reaſons for which it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that the Euchariſt ſhould conſiſt of Nouriſhment, of which I have ſpoken here above, and could alſo allege them for the Water of Baptiſm.</p>
                  <p>But we think further, wherefore were not thoſe Elements uſed in ſome
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:169751:67"/>
extraordinary faſhion; or why are they not ſent us from Heaven as the <hi>Manna;</hi> or produced miraculouſly as the Wine at the Mariage in <hi>Cana?</hi> Or why was there not ſome Miracle ſhewed, as in the Loaves which Jeſus Chriſt multiplyed for the ſatisfying of many thouſands of perſons? Or why hath not the bread of the Holy Supper the vertue of ſuſtaining us forty dayes after, without eating or drinking, as that which God cauſed to be brought to <hi>Elias?</hi> And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, why did not an Angell deſcend into the water of Baptiſm, as in the pool of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> for to heal corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall maladies? Why was <hi>Naaman</hi> healed of his Leproſy in the water of <hi>Jordan;</hi> and nevertheleſs if a Leaper be Baptized, his Leproſy is not wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped away?</p>
                  <p>To all this may be given one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon anſwer touching the cauſes of the Ceſſation of miracles. But there are particulars touching our Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:169751:67"/>
by name touching the Supper. The end of a miracle, is to ſhew the greatneſs and power of God: On the contrary, the end of our Sacraments, particularly of the Euchariſt, is to ſhew the infirmity, the death and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation of Chriſt. Now the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace could not be repreſented by a glorious ſpectacle and full of ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour; nor the weakneſs by tokens of infinite power, ſuch as miracles are; nor the death and paſſion, by acts of an unchangeable life; nor the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation of the Humanity, by the glorious demonſtrations of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature. Therefore it is that our Saviour who had multiplied the bread and turned the Water into Wine, at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feaſts, and for other occaſions, hath done nothing ſo in this here, but makes uſe of Bread and Wine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced naturally, and ſuch as they are in their ordinary proprieties, without adding thereto any thing miraculous. This ought to render the tales which
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:169751:68"/>
men make of apparitions and other wonders ſeen in the Euchariſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſuſpected. For it is credible that if our Saviour would have au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized it by miracles, he would have rather employed them in the firſt Supper, when the eſtabliſhing of the New Sacrament was in agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Finally, as the Sacraments which were inſtituted to be ordinary and perpetuall in the Judaicall Church, <hi>viz.</hi> the Circumciſion and the Paſſeover, had nothing ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall; So the Sacraments which at this day take place of thoſe, and which are ordinary and perpetuall in the Chriſtian Church, ought not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in extraordinary and miraculous ſigns or operations. Moreover the Euchariſt ſucceeded the eating of Sacrifices, which was truly a ſacred action, but wherein no miracle did intervene. And laſtly, becauſe men have uſed to turn into idols the ſigns whereby God hath produced ſome
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:169751:68"/>
wonder, (witneſs the Brazen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent) or to make a ſtay there, as if the Grace and power of God were there incloſed: if he had given us Sacraments of a more illuſtrious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, or if ſome miracle had been done thereby, long agoe Superſtition would have deified them; which yet is not left undone.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:169751:69"/>
               <head>The Fourth Sect. Wherein are handled certain points concerning the practice of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in the receiving of the Supper.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of our ignorance or errors in ſome Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the death of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe doctrine of the Roman Church bears in its conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, That a man may eat the body of Jeſus Chriſt without knowing or thinking of it. For it may happen that an hoſt fallen into the hands of ſuch an one, who knowing not that it was conſecrated may ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it down, and remain ignorant of its being Jeſus Chriſt. And though
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:169751:69"/>
he ſhould think it, he would not know how to make it evident; ſith that if he ſhould put it into ſcales, againſt one that were not conſecrated, this would be found to weigh as much as the other. Finally, a mouſe which devoures the hoſt thinks not to eat a Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>But this is an aſſured Maxim to us, That the fleſh of Jeſus Chriſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be eaten, without knowing of it or thinking of it. From whence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that whoſoever knows not Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is incapable of this eating. Now I need not repeat that which is notorious to all, whereto at the leaſt ought to extend the knowledge of a Chriſtian; but only to ſpeak of that which I have laid down in chief. The end of the Supper is, that we declare the death of the Lord. This requires the hiſtoricall intelligence of the particularities of it, whereof none is of any ſmall importance. For it is not enough to know in generall or ſummarily that Jeſus Chriſt is
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:169751:70"/>
dead; but we muſt have a diſtinct knowledge of the place, time, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumſtances of his death. It is not in vain that the Holy Spirit hath ſo carefully marked them. They are all as ſo many ſtars to guide us in the ſearch of our ſalvation, and have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one ſome particular influence. Nevertheleſs if a Chriſtian compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend them not exactly, this igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (ſo that it be not wilfull) will not hinder but he may communicate to ſalvation. It is a point which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports us, to know how long our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour was on the Croſs. The du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his laſt ſufferings is conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable in all ſorts. It is alſo repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented more than once in holy Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, <hi>viz.</hi> in St. <hi>Mark</hi> 15. v. 25. &amp; 33. and in St. <hi>John</hi> 19. v. 14. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs all Chriſtians underſtand it not. For ſome with more ground hold that Jeſus Chriſt was upon the Croſs for the ſpace of three hours; Others double the time, and believe he remained there ſix hours. Now as
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:169751:70"/>
tis known this difference comes from this, that the Evangeliſts having u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed divers terms to expreſs the ſame thing, expoſitors have taken them diverſly.</p>
                  <p>But if we did know perfectly all the circumſtances of this death, wee ſhould not know all the particular reaſons, nor all the myſteries there contained. As for Example; upon that which was obſerved that our Saviour gave up the Ghoſt at the hour of the Evening Sacrifice, there are few who think of that which is ſaid in the 9. of <hi>Daniel</hi> v. 21. to wit, that the hour wherein the Angell decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the time of the death of Chriſt to come, many ages before, was that of the Evening Sacrifice; which is to be admired, and full of Conſolation.</p>
                  <p>Now our ignorance in ſuch matters is no ſmall fault. And we ought not to flatter our ſelves with this pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Maxim of the vulgar, <hi>viz.</hi> wee have no need of ſo much knowledge. But on the other ſide, a Chriſtian who
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:169751:71"/>
ſtrives to inſtruct himſelf more and more ought not to think that theſe omiſſions which he is forced to make up, doe deprive him of the ſaving Communion of the Sacrament. Not without cauſe doth the ſcripture give us to know that even the Apoſtles themſelves when Jeſus Chriſt gave them the Euchariſt with his own hands, were defiled with notable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours. <hi>Luke.</hi> 22. <hi>v.</hi> 24. And it is certain that we know more of the myſtery of this Sacrament, and underſtand better the grounds of this doctrine, and the cauſes of the death of Chriſt Jeſus, than his diſciples did, when they were admitted to that firſt ſupper.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:169751:71"/>
                  <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Why doth not the reading of the Paſsion of Jeſus Chriſt move us ſo much as the reading of many other hiſtories of the Scripture.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WEE know that the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the death of Jeſus Chriſt which wee declare in the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ought not to be naked and idle, or to remain in the Brain. It muſt deſcend into the heart, and ſtir up the affections. Now there is nothing which ought to move us equally with the Paſſion of the ſon of God<hi>:</hi> and the leaſt of his anguiſhes ought to be more ſenſible unto us than thoſe of all men together. Nevertheleſſe if wee read that ſad preparation of <hi>Abraham</hi> going to ſacrifize his ſon; or the pitifull words of <hi>Jacob,</hi> when they told him that ſome beaſt had devoured Joſeph; or the ſacking of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by the Babylonians, yea
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:169751:72"/>
how they handled that miſerable King <hi>Zedekias,</hi> wee are touched more lively, and theſe ſtories will draw more teares from our eyes, than the hiſtory of the ſuffrings of Jeſus Chriſt. And as there are tears of joy, they will ſooner fall from our eyes in reading how <hi>Joſeph</hi> met with his brothers, and of the cry which he caſt forth when he made himſelf known unto them, than in hearing of Chriſt comming forth of the ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre, and the joy which his Diſciples had to ſee him riſen again. Yet ſo it is, that neither the knife which was to cut <hi>Jſaacks</hi> throat, nor the bloody coat of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> nor the deſolations and crying in the ſtreets of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> are not to us of ſuch importance as the ſuffrings of the ſon of God. And his Reſurrection is more conſiderable to us than the exaltation of <hi>Joſeph.</hi> For to reſolve this queſtion wee have divers things to conſider.</p>
                  <p>Firſt the ſuffrings of thoſe who were but men, doe eaſily move us,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:169751:72"/>
becauſe there is nothing more natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall than to have a fellow-feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Calamities of thoſe who are like us; but the griefes of Jeſus Chriſt preſent themſelves unto us in a perſon which cannot be the object of any commiſeration or naturall commotion. For wee think of God himſelf ſuffring in form of a ſervant. This is the reaſon wherefore he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad the tears of thoſe who bewailed him as a man whoſe affliction is pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied, or the loſſe of whom is much lamented, <hi>Luke.</hi> 23. <hi>v.</hi> 28.</p>
                  <p>Whereupon it is that the hiſtory of the Paſſion is not written in a pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and pathetick ſtyle, as the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> or the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of <hi>David</hi> over <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than;</hi> or the ulcers of <hi>Job;</hi> or the ſad ſolitude of the <hi>Jſraelites</hi> by the Rivers of <hi>Babylon.</hi> For the Goſpell doth not propound unto us a ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of human calamity, but a point of higher conſideration.</p>
                  <p>Moreover this condoling which
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:169751:73"/>
hath place in other ſubjects, is found either excluded or ſwallowed up in this here, by more noble and more ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall motions, as are the horrour of our ſins which have crucified the Prince of glory; the terrour of that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeverity which God hath diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon his own Son; the admiration of his incomparable wiſedome, who could joyn his Mercy with his Juſtice; the unſpeakable joy of ſalvation which is derived from thence unto us; and the ardent Love which wee bear to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Father who hath given his Son, and towards the Son who hath given himſelf to death for us. For theſe are the true reſentments which wee ought to have of the ſuffrings of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Now the ſubject of the ſpirituall reſentments is not naturally percep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible of our affections, but is a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger unto them. Therefore it is that they are not moved towards it but as they are drawn unto it by the finger of God. And even this is the cauſe
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:169751:73"/>
they are not carried thither with ſo full a vigour, and ſo much readineſs, as towards thoſe objects whereto they are enclineable of themſelves.</p>
                  <p>Moreover the ſpirituall affections, although they are ſtrong and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are not ſo eaſy to be moved and to be felt. For foraſmuch as they lodge as it were in the center of the Soul, they are far from the ſenſitive faculty, which is the ſource of tears: ſo that they come not thither ſo ſoon nor ſo eaſily. That which I have yet to ſay belongs to the queſtion follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:169751:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:169751:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:169751:75"/>
                  <head>CHAP. III. <hi>From whence comes it that the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious are ſometimes more moved with the Death of Jeſus Chriſt, than true Chriſtians.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WEE ſee ſometimes Idolaters who, having but very little underſtanding in the myſteries of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, will weep at the reciting of the Paſſion of Jeſus Chriſt; And nevertheleſſe a well-inſtructed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and who prizes the Suffrings of his Saviour a great deal more than they that are ignorant, will very hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be moved with it. This difference proceeds hence, that the Superſtitious have before their faces the Paſſion of Jeſus Chriſt as a tragicall accident, which doth eaſily touch thoſe hearts that are endued with any humanity. But the Chriſtian contemplates it with another eye than that wherewith we regard the Calamities of other men.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:169751:75"/>
The one brings thereunto an humane Commiſeration, which tears doe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally follow: But the other finds there the ſubject of many ſpirituall affections, whereof our heart is not ſo eaſily ſuſceptible, becauſe they proceed not from fleſh and blood. And the means of framing them to it conſiſt rather in inſtructions and doctrines whereby wee muſt handle this matter, than in the oratoricall repreſentations of thoſe who reduce it into a Tragedy.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, it is not an aſſured proof that he bears moſt Love towards Jeſus Chriſt that ſhal have ſhed moſt tears for him. For oftentimes they proceed as ſoon fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a tender-heartednes which is more naturall to ſome than others, as from the abundance of piety. Many who never wept for the love of Chriſt, nevertheleſs ſuffered Martyrdome for the love of him. Such a one could not give him ſo much as one Tear, who gave him all his Blood.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:169751:76"/>
                  <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Off the vehemency of the thoughts, and of the attention required in the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Communion. And of the weakneſſe of the humane ſpirit herein.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I doe not here refute thoſe, who for want of well underſtanding our Doctrine, think that the ſpirituall Communion of the Body or Chriſt conſiſts onely in thought of imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: we could object unto them the Souls which they believe to be in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, which according to the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Roman Church enjoy the Communion of Chriſt, and ſo of his Fleſh and Blood. A Communion which cannot be otherwiſe than in ſpirit. For theſe Souls have neither mouth nor ſtomack.</p>
                  <p>Neither doe I content my ſelf with that which is alleged for proof of the true Communion; that ſometimes
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:169751:76"/>
ſome have fallen into an Extaſy in the receiving their hoſt, through admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of pretended wonders which they there preſuppoſe. Such Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſmes are neither ſufficient, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the Communion of the Body of Chriſt. For although it be ſupernaturall: yet notwithſtanding it is not done by a miraculous tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, nor by a motion ſo vehement, as that of the Prophets when they were raviſhed in Spirit, untill they had even loſt their ſence and remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unmoveable; all the functions of the ſoul (except in thoſe of the Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect) being at that time in their inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſs we know that a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ought to bring the moſt ſtrong and vehement thoughts that he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſo high a myſtery. All other cogitations ought to be ſuſpended, all other objects excluded. But it comes to paſs often that a Chriſtian, after having duly prepared himſelf for the Holy Supper, will find himſelf all on
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:169751:77"/>
the ſudden and unawares ſurpriſed with doubts and ſcruples, at the ſame moment when he receives the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt. I omit the inadvertencies, the extravagancies, and the enormous thoughts which overtake men in this action. Theſe phantaſms poſſeſs the place which ought to be reſerved en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire for Jeſus Chriſt: and although men ſtrive to drive them away, it is never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs impoſſible for them. This ſhews that a human ſpirit is not Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of it ſelf, ſith that it cannot ſtop its own thoughts, and that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend not on his will. Now although they are not voluntary, nevertheleſs ſith that they are ours, and that they croſs the attention which is due to an action of ſo great importance, they offend the dignity of the body of Chriſt. And in this alſo is ſeen the infirmity of man, who ſins even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Sacrifice which brings him the remiſsion of his ſins. But if he condemn theſe evill cogitations, if he ſtrive to ſcare them as <hi>Abraham</hi>
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:169751:77"/>
did the Birds of prey which came to devour his Sacrifice; although (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this) they intervene in the inſtant and at the very act of the eating of the Sacrament, Jeſus Chriſt will not refuſe to lodge in the ſoul of this weak Chriſtian. For he who is dead for our tranſgreſſions, hath alſo expiated thoſe which we commit even in applying this expiation unto our ſelves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. V. <hi>That the act of the Communion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not in mourning for the death of Chriſt, but rather in joy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of Spirit.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THere is no need of diſputing whether the faithfull who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before the paſſion of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, had reaſon to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed, not knowing whether they ought to wiſh that the Son might ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:169751:78"/>
death, or rather deſire with St. <hi>Peter,</hi> that this might not happen unto him. They were invited to the one, for the Love of their Salvation; and to the other, as it ſeems, for the Love of their Saviour. Our Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided this queſtion, both before his death by that ſharp cenſure which he made of it to his Diſciples, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards when he alleged the Oracles importing that Jeſus Chriſt muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, to the end he might enter into his glory.</p>
                  <p>But it may be demanded whether the Holy Supper be an action of joy or rather of ſadneſs. Certainly the death of Jeſus Chriſt, wherein we declare the horrible anguiſhes of his Soul, the ſtrokes of that holy Body broken with griefs, the effuſion of that innocent blood which we there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider as if it were powred forth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, are a ſubiect of Sadneſs unto us. And that for aſmuch more as acknowledging our ſelves to be the cauſe of his ſufferings, we cannot
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:169751:78"/>
but be touched with regrete that we have procured them. Now theſe reſentments ſeem to exclude from our minds all manner of Joy in the act of the Communion. The Law for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bade the putting of incenſe and oyl, which is the Symbol of Joy, upon the Fleſh ſacrificed for ſins. And the Jews at this day obſerve ſo preciſely, that which heretofore was enjoyned them in the feaſt of expiations, <hi>viz.</hi> to afflict their ſouls; that on all that day they refrain from reading even any paſſage of Scripture which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains any matter of joy; as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming forth out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Canaan, &amp;c.</hi> On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, their reading is of nothing but ſorrowfull things, as are the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the curſings of the Law, and ſuch like points.</p>
                  <p>But omitting that which might be ſaid of this Superſtition, there is none who knows not that the Euchariſt is an acknowledgement of a benefit which is offered unto us in this action,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:169751:79"/>
which we cannot receive but with joy. Alſo this Sacrament is inſtituted for our conſolation. True it is we ought to come unto it with ſadneſs, for the Reaſons above ſaid; That is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary fore runner: But the proper act, wherein lyes the Communion or reception of the Body of Chriſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts not in that; but in the joy and contentment which our Soul receives in that Jeſus Chriſt hath given him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for it. The Superſtitious deceive themſelves who believe that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of his death conſiſts one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in much mourning. For in the Euchariſt Jeſus Chriſt is not ſimply propounded unto us as dead, but as dead for us. To the end that as his death is our life, ſo it ſhould be alſo our joy.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:169751:79"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of an advantage which we have above thoſe of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>in the inſtruction required for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and of the diſtinctions, which the Orthodox obſerve in this matter of the Sacrament.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Roman Catholick hath need of a great deal more time to learn his Religion, than one that is Orthodox hath to underſtand his.</p>
                  <p>Let a man behold a volume wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is compriſed the whole Roman Religion, as the Doctors thereof have reduced their Divinity into one Body; he ſhall ſee that it much ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth the ordinary bulk of thoſe wherein ours is contained. For I ſpeak not here of writings of Controverſy; ſith that Faith conſiſts not in the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of Errors, but in the Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of Truths. It is to be underſtood of poſitive Divinity; whoſe extent
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:169751:80"/>
if it be compared with that of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, theirs wilbe found much more vaſt and ſwelling than ours. Their Religion is compoſed of a greater number of articles: For they have many which our Theology doth not acknowledge; and in thoſe which are common to us both, they have heaped up a number of matters which alſo our Religion nullifies. Briefly the Roman Theology contains al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all our Affirmative, but over and above that which it profeſſeth to acknowledge with us, it hath its own additions. From thence it comes that that is more prolix than ours.</p>
                  <p>This is ſeen above all, in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Sacraments, wherein the learned of the Roman Church are more copious than in other points. For amongſt them almoſt all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is reduc'd to Sacraments, and the Grounds of their Divinity conſiſt in this matter. Moreover as they have multiplyed the Sacraments even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:169751:80"/>
the number of ſeaven, they have need of more ſtuffs to cloath them, than we who have but two. And as for the Euchariſt, beſides that which they hold with us, they have added to the Sacrament the Expiatory Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; to the ſpirituall eating of the body of Chriſt, the eating with the mouth; to the Analogy between the ſign and the thing ſignified, the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation of the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; to the adoration of Chriſt, the adoration of the Sacrament it ſelf; and of other additions which have infinite conſequences, all which enter together hudled up in this point of the Euchariſt. And as they are full of Labyrinths, and rugged wayes, wherein we cannot walk without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther endangering Faith or Naturall Reaſon, or ſence; The Roman Church hath conceived many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, which it gives for marks and directions to walk by in aſſurance. Now the multitude alone of them
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:169751:81"/>
(leaving all that may be ſaid of them otherwiſe) ſhews that an Orthodox will ſooner learn all that he ought to believe of the Euchariſt, than a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick will the tenth part of that which his Religion teacheth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this point.</p>
                  <p>Nine diſtinctions, ſuch as are theſe following, will clear to us all this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs. We put a difference between a Sacrament and a Figure. Every Sacrament is a Figure, but every Sign is not a Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>Between the Sacramentall eating and the Spirituall eating; The one regards the Signs, the other the thing ſignified.</p>
                  <p>Between the Subſtantiall being of Sacraments, and their Significative being. The Bread is the Body of Chriſt Sacramentally, as the rock was Chriſt, that is to ſay in a myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſignification.</p>
                  <p>Between Reall and Corporall. All that is Corporall is Reall: but all
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:169751:81"/>
that is Reall is not Corporall. Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall actions amongſt which is the eating of the Body of Chriſt are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all but not Corporall.</p>
                  <p>Between the divers manners of Preſence. Many things are preſent to the Memory, and to the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which are not to the Corporall ſences. Many objects are even pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to us corporally, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from us, by a greater diſtance of places; witneſſe the Sun and the Stars.</p>
                  <p>Between the divers degrees of our Conjunction with Chriſt; which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in three regards, is either Naturall, or Myſticall, or Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
                  <p>Between Faith and the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Body of Chriſt. Faith is not the Communion, but the Organ by which it is made.</p>
                  <p>Between a Sacrament and a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. The Sacrament is a gift which God beſtowes on man, Sacrifice is a
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:169751:82"/>
preſent man which makes to God. In the Euchariſt it is not Man who offers Jeſus Chriſt to God; but it is God who offers Jeſus Chriſt to Man.</p>
                  <p>Between a Sacrifice of Expiation, and a Sacrifice of Thanksgiving. This is done in the Euchariſt, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was done onely on the Croſs.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:169751:82"/>
               <head>The Fift Section. Which is the ſubject of a greater treatiſe ſerving not onely for the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Euchariſt, but alſo of all the New Teſtament.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Style of the New Teſtament is wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and compoſed of ſix kindes of Phraſes and terms of different ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BY theſe termes and ſpeeches I underſtand not (after the order of Grammarians) the ſound of words, or their Etymologies in the tongue wherein the New Teſtament is written; but rather the ſenſe and ſubject of expreſſions employed in it. They come therefore from divers Sources, to wit,</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="146" facs="tcp:169751:83"/>
1. Either from the common uſe of men, which is as it were a language univerſall to all Nations. As are the termes which repreſent the objects and the acts of ſenſe; Fire, water, the ſun, the head, the feet, eating, drinking; and generally all that is naturally and ordinarily known to men. For the new Teſtament touches many things of this Nature either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly, or occaſionally.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or from the Old Teſtament; which is either cited, or explaned, or applied in the New.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Or from the 27 Interpreters, who having tranſlated the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into Greek, before the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Jeſus Chriſt, have often ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the Hebrew by certain phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes particular to themſelves; which are alſo entred into the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe that the Apoſtles did often employ this Tranſlation, which was very common in their time.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Or from the Divinity or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Diſcipline of the antient
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:169751:83"/>
Jews, of their Synagogue, Policy &amp;c. This Divinity being the ſame with that of the Prophets. But to make it more intelligible, and more eaſily to prevent hereſies, the Jewiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors introduced termes which were not in the Old Teſtament, ſignifying nevertheleſs the ſame things in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. Or elſe they had transferred by analogy ſome words of the Old Teſtament beyond their ordinary ſignification. Now Jeſus Chriſt and the Apoſtles have retained them in part in the New Teſtament.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Or from the Morality of the Greeks, and their Arts, Proverbes and Sentences, many of their termes are in the New Teſtament, becauſe the greateſt part of the Gentiles to whom the Goſpell was preached at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, were either Greeks by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or ſeaſoned with the wiſedom and cuſtome of the Greeks.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Or from the Style particular to the New Teſtament. For beſides the expreſſions drawn from the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:169751:84"/>
fountaines, Jeſus Chriſt and the Apoſtles have alſo many others, which are proper and particular unto them.</p>
                  <p>All this wilbe cleared by the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing examples already obſerved by the Expoſitors; whereunto I have added ſome few which my obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations have furniſhed me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Termes of the common Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of men.</head>
                     <p>THeſe examples are infinite in number, and the common ſenſe will make them manifeſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. When Jeſus Chriſt ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Thomas, Put thy hand into my ſide.</hi> When he commanded the Diſciples to <hi>caſt the net on the right ſide of the ſhip.</hi> And thoſe which were about the Sepulcher of <hi>Lazarus, to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſtone which was at the going in.</hi> All theſe ſpeeches, and a thouſand others the like, bear ſimply the ſenſe
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:169751:84"/>
which they have in the ordinary lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; and there ought not any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be given them, as doe they who diſguiſe them by allegories; ſaying that Jeſus Chriſt ſpake of the Abſolution of ſinners, when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that <hi>Lazarus</hi> which was newly riſen again ſhould be unbound.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Terms of the old Teſtament.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THE finger of God Luke.</hi> 11. ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies his mervelous power, ſo expreſſed in <hi>Exod.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 19.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hee who is, who was, and who is to to come, Revel.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 4. This is the expreſſion of the name <hi>Jehovah,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planed in <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 14. <hi>Eheje,</hi> I am that I am, or that ſhalbe.</p>
                     <p>The Concluſion of the Lords Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>for thine is the kingdome &amp;c.</hi> is taken from the ſeventh of <hi>Daniel. v.</hi> 14. and to him was given Dominion, Glory and Kingdome &amp;c. and his Dominion is everlaſting.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="150" facs="tcp:169751:85"/>
Many <hi>Hebrew</hi> words, as <hi>Hallelujah, Amen,</hi> come alſo from the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Terms of the</hi> 70 <hi>Interpreters.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>I Touch not here the paſſages of the Old Teſtament which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated in the New with ſome difference, as being ſo found in the Tranſlation of the Septuagint, which the Apoſtles have retained in many places. The particulars and queſtions which may be moved thereupon, have paſſed the examination of the learned.</p>
                     <p>Wee will obſerve onely for a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern that the word <hi>Prophet,</hi> the word <hi>Church,</hi> and divers others, are come from the Seventy, who have employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them in the Greek Traſlation of the Old Teſtnament from whence they are paſſed into the New.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="151" facs="tcp:169751:85"/>
                     <head>Terms of the Divinity and Diſcipline of the Jews</head>
                     <p>THE names of <hi>Paradiſe</hi> and of <hi>Gehenna</hi> are not in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the ſenſe which they have in the New <hi>viz.</hi> to denote the places of Joy and Torment after this life. Neither doe wee there read theſe words, <hi>The world to come, The day of Judgment, The ſecond death, The bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of Abraham,</hi> and others which are come from the Judaicall ſchool, which had put them into uſe againſt the Sadduces, denying the immortality of ſouls, and the points which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſe it.</p>
                     <p>Now Jeſus Chriſt hath ſanctified theſe terms, and would have them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted into the New Teſtament.</p>
                     <p>The Jews before the comming of the Meſſias were wont in their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to pray for the Comming of the kingdom of God. Jeſus Chriſt alſo hath put this Petition into the prayer
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:169751:86"/>
which he hath taught us.</p>
                     <p>The ſame Jews ſpeaking of this Kingdom of the Meſſias which they expected, called it the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Now they had drawn this phraſe from hence, that in <hi>Daniel</hi> this Kingdom was repreſented under the figure of Starrs, Chap. 8. <hi>v.</hi> 10. And on the contrary the Empires of this world were ſet forth under the form of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beaſts. This name of the Kingdom of Heaven, as uſed among the Jews, is alſo frequent in the mouth of the Son of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Terms from the Morality of the Greeks.</head>
                     <p>THis is very remarkable, the word <hi>VERTUE,</hi> inaſmuch as it ſignifieth the habit of good manners, is not found in the Old Teſtament. For the Hebrews have no term which anſwers preciſely to this here. The Greek word which hath the ſame ſignification is uſed
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:169751:86"/>
in the New Teſtament, yet very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, for reaſons whoſe conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on belongs to another diſcourſe.</p>
                     <p>Likewiſe we have the particular names of many Vertues, as alſo of many Vices which are not read in the Old Teſtament. Such are the words of <hi>Temperance,</hi> of <hi>Chaſtity,</hi> and divers others; which alſo come from the Morall of the Greeks.</p>
                     <p>Even from thence is come the word of <hi>Almes,</hi> which is not alſo in the Old Teſtament. The Hebrews expreſs it by a more generall name. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>Almes,</hi> they ſay Juſtice. From thence comes it that the Syriack tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating theſe words of S. <hi>Matthew</hi> 6. <hi>Give not your Almes before men, hath tranſlated, do not your Juſtice before men.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Terms particular to the New Teſtament.</head>
                     <p>I Will give but one example among many, The habitation of the moſt bleſſed is called the. <hi>Third Heaven,</hi>
                        <pb n="154" facs="tcp:169751:87"/>
2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. This name is not given to it in the Old Teſtament. The holy tongue, wherein <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers have written, naming the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, expreſſeth them in the duall number; as if it ſhould be ſaid <hi>the two Heavens.</hi> The name of the <hi>third</hi> is come up thereupon, only ſince that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is entred therein. I omit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contemplations which may be brought hitherto.</p>
                     <p>Finally all the writers of the New Teſtament, have alſo every one his ſtyle, and particular terms, whereof it is not neceſſary to ſpeak at this time.</p>
                     <p>Now as of all theſe expreſſions whereof we have ſeen the Originals, ſome carry the proper ſenſe and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall to the terms, and others are drawn (by a figure) to a quite divers ſignification, ſo we ought alſo to ſee the matters where-from the figurative ſpeeches are extracted.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:169751:87"/>
                  <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The Figurative ſpeeches which are in the New Teſtament are taken from five divers ſorts of matters.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe way which we have here held above, is almoſt the ſame which conducts us hither. Every phraſe which bears a Figure in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, is drawn from ſome of theſe ſubjects here mentioned, or from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Either from things which are of the generall knowledge, and common to the moſt part of men.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or from matters of the Old Teſtament, as Waſhings, Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Or from Cuſtoms, Conditions and other things particular to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Jews, when Jeſus Chriſt and the Apoſtles were in the world.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Or from the Cuſtoms of thoſe of the Eaſtern people, Greeks and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:169751:88"/>
nations with whom the Church of God hath converſed heretofore.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Or even from the proper mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the New Teſtament, the one taking the name of the other.</p>
                  <p>The New Teſtament contains then five Orders or Categories of figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive terms, whereof wee muſt give ſome examples.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>I. <hi>Examples of the firſt Order.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Hence comes the ſimilitude of the <hi>Sower,</hi> of <hi>Leven,</hi> of <hi>Occupying, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Apoſtles are called the <hi>Salt of the Earth,</hi> God is called <hi>Light,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt is named the <hi>Vine, the Dove.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Holy Ghoſt is deſigned by the name of <hi>Water, of Fire.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>II. <hi>Examples of the ſecond Order.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Jeſus Chriſt is called the <hi>Tree of Life, the Manna, Rev.</hi> 2. <hi>The firſt fruits of thoſe that ſleep.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. Alms is called an <hi>Offering of a ſweet ſmelling</hi>
                        <pb n="157" facs="tcp:169751:88"/>
                        <hi>ſavour. Phil.</hi> 4. by a tearm bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from the perfumes that were uſed upon the Altar of Incenſe.</p>
                     <p>In this ranck are many alluſions<hi>:</hi> Jeſus Chriſt in St. <hi>Luke</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 42. upbraided Jeruſalem that they <hi>knew not the things which belonged to their peace, that it was hid from their eyes.</hi> The agreement which is found in theſe words, is not viſible to any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thoſe who know that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (in the language of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) ſignifies <hi>viſion of peace.</hi> For theſe words mean that quite contrary to her name <hi>ſhe ſaw not her peace, that Jerſulalem was not in Jeruſalem.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Some Hebraiſms may be referd hither. In the 13. of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> when the Law would ſay <hi>that the Prieſt ſhall pronounce him clean who was healed of the Leproſy, it ſaith, that the Prieſt ſhall cleanſe him;</hi> and when it would ſay, That the Prieſt ſhall declare ſuch a one defiled with a Leproſy, it ſaith, <hi>the Prieſt ſhall defile him.</hi> So Jeſus Chriſt ſaith <hi>that his Diſciples ſhall</hi>
                        <pb n="158" facs="tcp:169751:89"/>
                        <hi>pardon or retain ſins,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>ſhall pronounce that they are pardoned or retained.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="part">
                     <head>III. <hi>Examples of the third Order.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Parable of the Virgins; of the Children fitting in the market-places, and divers others, taken from the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of the Jews.</p>
                     <p>The Degrees of puniſhments uſed among them, <hi>viz. Of Judgement, of the Counſell, and of Hell fire,</hi> are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for to repreſent the difference of pains whereunto God condemneth ſinners, <hi>Matthew</hi> 5.</p>
                     <p>Our Saviour ſaith that one <hi>Iota</hi> or one <hi>Jod</hi> of the Law, that is to ſay the leaſt article of it, ſhall not paſs away without being accompliſhed. This word is taken from the Alphabet of the Hebrews, whereof the leaſt letter of all is called <hi>Jod.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 22. denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth <hi>Maranatha</hi> againſt whomſoever loved not the Lord Jeſus, This was
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:169751:89"/>
the term of the greater Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion uſed among the Jews.</p>
                     <p>The Scribes and interpreters of the Law had the Key of the Cheſts and <hi>Archives</hi> where were kept the ſacred books. To this our Saviour makes alluſion, when he upbraids them with having withdrawn the Key of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and not to have entred into it.</p>
                     <p>When a Doctor of the Law was created, they ſpake to him after this manner, as the <hi>Rabbines</hi> relate it; <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Authority to pronounce bound whatſoever ſhall be bound, and to pronounce unbound whatſoever ſhalbe unbound.</hi> This explains the words of Jeſus Chriſt ſpeaking to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, whom he would conſtitute Doctors: <hi>That which yee bind on earth, ſhalbe bound in Heaven, and that which ye ſhall unbind on earth, ſhalbe unbound in Heaven.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the 3. of the <hi>Revel.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt promiſeth to them that ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, <hi>that they ſhall walk with him in white Rayments.</hi> Theſe White ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:169751:90"/>
ſay we, are the token of purity and innocence; But ſome learned men have obſerved that this term was taken from a formality uſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Jews, when any one was inſtalled into the Prieſthood. For the Councill having examined the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogy and other qualities required in him who pretended to this charge; if he were judged incapable, they ſent him back clad with a black robe, to ſignify that he was rejected from the Altar. But if he gained his cauſe, they clad him with a white robe, which was the habit of the Prieſts, and he entred the Temple with his Colleagues. Our Saviour ſeems to have a regard to this Cuſtom, when hee promiſes the <hi>white Garment</hi> to thoſe whom he made Prieſts, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures them that they ſhall walk with him. <hi>Revel.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 6.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="part">
                     <pb n="161" facs="tcp:169751:90"/>
                     <head>IIII. <hi>Examples of the fourth Order.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>In St. <hi>Mathew</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 41. Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>if any one compell thee to goe a mile,</hi> &amp;c. where the word tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated <hi>(Compell)</hi> ſignifies <hi>to conſtrain one to run poſt;</hi> The word came from the <hi>Perſians,</hi> who called thoſe <hi>(An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gari)</hi> whom wee call Poſts or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
                     <p>In the <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>the white ſtone</hi> is taken from the manner whereby the Greeks and the antient Romans gave their voyces in Criminall Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>The black ſtone was</hi> the mark of Condemnation, <hi>The white</hi> of the contrary.</p>
                     <p>I omit the ſimilitudes drawn from the <hi>Iſtthmian</hi> ſports and the like, <hi>viz.</hi> from the Race, from the <hi>Wraſtling,</hi> from the <hi>Combates</hi> of the <hi>Amphithea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre,</hi> and other Cuſtoms of the Greeks. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> &amp; chap. 15. <hi>v.</hi> 32.</p>
                     <p>In <hi>Revel.</hi> 16. It is foretold that the River <hi>Euphrates</hi> ſhould be dryed up,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:169751:91"/>
that the way of the Kings and people of the Eaſt might be prepared. It is an alluſion to the Stratagem whereby <hi>Cyrus</hi> made himſelf maſter of the City of <hi>Babylon,</hi> having diverted the River <hi>Euphrates</hi> by many little chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels.</p>
                     <p>In divers places of the <hi>Revelation</hi> our Saviour expreſſing the beginning and the end of all things, takes the name of <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> which are the firſt and the laſt Letters of the Greek Alphabet.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="part">
                     <head>V. <hi>Examples of the fift Order.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The phraſe which imports <hi>that we are Crucified to the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> is borrowed from the kind of death that Jeſus Chriſt ſuffered. Many things which are ſaid properly of his perſon, are transferred to his Church; as when it is ſaid, <hi>that we ſhall come to the age of perfect man, and the meaſure of the perfect ſtature of Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the 13. of St. <hi>Luke</hi> the Parable
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:169751:91"/>
ſaith, <hi>theſe three years I come ſeeking fruit of this fig tree and find none.</hi> Some Chronologers obſerve, that Jeſus Chriſt makes alluſion to the time of his miniſtry. For when he pronounced theſe words, he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready preached three years to the people of the Jews, exhorting them to bear fruit.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The term of eating uſed to ſignify the Communion of the Body of Chriſt, is in the ſecond Order of Figurative Speeches.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ONe and the ſame figure may be taken from divers matters; and ſo one and the ſame phraſe may be found in divers rancks, in divers regards; but in the one more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly than in the other. The point it ſelf, for the underſtanding whereof I have laid down theſe diſtinctions, will
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:169751:92"/>
explain that which I intend to ſay.</p>
                  <p>When the Communion of the Body of Chriſt is expreſſed by the word of <hi>Eating,</hi> this phraſe is not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and immediatly drawn from this act naturall and common to all men, yea to other living Creatures, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we take our nouriſhment; but of the action of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating of the Fleſh of Sacrifices and other ſacred meats. An action which was truly naturall <hi>Materially,</hi> if we may ſo ſpeak, ſith that it conſiſted in eating; but <hi>Formally</hi> and <hi>properly</hi> it was a ſacred action, and a point of the Ceremoniall Law. So that this ſpeech, <hi>to eat the Body of Chriſt</hi> is amongſt thoſe which are drawn from the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Old Teſtament. The which appears alſo (not to repeat all that which I have ſaid before) in that Jeſus Chriſt hath retained the terms of it. For among others, ſpeaking of his Blood, he explains himſelf after the manner of the words of <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Exod.</hi> 24. <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>Behold the Blood of</hi>
                     <pb n="165" facs="tcp:169751:92"/>
                     <hi>the Covenant.</hi> I ſhall conclude this with a very notable conſideration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Why doe the two Sacraments of the Chriſtian Church conſiſt the one in Waſhing, the other in Nouriſhment.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WE uſe to ſay that theſe are two ſimilitudes or analogies, wherein our Saviour hath ſhut theſe two Sacramennts; becauſe that the waſhing and the eating repreſent very properly the application of Jeſus Chriſt, who is a ſpirituall waſhing and nouriſhment unto us. But this reaſon goes not far enough in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of our Saviour. The Water is employed in Baptiſm, not ſimply becauſe of its naturall propriety of waſhing and cleanſing, but for a more particular Reaſon. Likewiſe the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritive vertue which is in the Bread, and in the Wine, is not the onely
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:169751:93"/>
cauſe, nor the immediate cauſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were choſen for ſigns of the Body and Blood of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>We muſt therefore know, that in the old time under the Law, amongſt the Acts which repreſented the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of future Redemption, there were two common and ordinary, <hi>viz. Waſhing</hi> and <hi>Eating.</hi> There were indeed but theſe two acts, whereby the people participated of Holy things. For they were exhibited to them either in Waſhing; as the Water of ſprinkling, and the Blood where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they beſprinckled unclean per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: or in Nouriſhment; as the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chall Lamb, the Fleſh of Euchariſtick Sacrifices, and other food ſanctified by the Law. Alſo the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> Chap. 9. <hi>v.</hi> 10. teacheth us that all theſe legall matters conſiſted either in waſhings or in meats and drinks.</p>
                  <p>Now this ſhews clearly why Jeſus Chriſt hath Inſtituted the Sacraments to the number of two; and why in
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:169751:93"/>
theſe two manners above-ſaid, the one of <hi>Waſhing,</hi> the other of <hi>Nouriſhment.</hi> It is to the end that the ſame acts which had in times paſt repreſented the Application of Jeſus Chriſt in theſe two divers regards, ſhould ſtill repreſent it.</p>
                  <p>This Application was truly figured alſo by the Circumciſion, whereto Baptiſm ſucceeded: But we have ſeen that our Sacraments ought not to have any more any thing bloody. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, as I ſaid, Our Saviour ſeems to have regard to this point, that all holy things, thoſe which the Law made communicable to every one of the people, were applied perſonally unto him in the one or in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe two actions onely, <hi>viz.</hi> either in their <hi>Waſhings,</hi> or in their <hi>Sacred Banquets;</hi> To theſe two ſorts of actions, wherein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts all the participation of holy things anſwer Baptiſm and the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt. If we contemplate there but a reſemblance between the Water, the
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:169751:94"/>
Bread and the Wine, of the one part, and the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt of the other; this conſideration is too wandring and generall, and doth not obſerve diſtinctly enough the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of our Saviour. Wee know that the Communion of Jeſus Chriſt is repreſented in Scripture under the Similitude of divers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onjunctions; as of the Head with the Members; of the Vine with the Branches; of the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band with the Wife; of the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the edifice; of the Clothing with the Body; of Waſhing, and of Nouriſhment. But it is a queſtion to know why among ſo many ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, our Saviour would chooſe theſe two, <hi>viz.</hi> that of <hi>Waſhing,</hi> and that of <hi>Nouriſhment,</hi> rather than any other, whereof to make the Sacraments of the New Teſtament. I believe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt ſeek the reaſon in the correſpondence which they have with theſe two actions of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein only lyes the perſonall application of holy things which the Law diſtributed to the people.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="169" facs="tcp:169751:94"/>
To Conclude, I ſhall adde touching the Water of Baptiſm, that which I ſaid touching the Bread and the Wine of the Euchariſt. Many Divines diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute Philoſophically of the proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Water, by reaſon whereof our Saviour would it ſhould ſerve for Baptiſm. For (ſay they) as Water or watery matter is the principall of all naturall production, ſo the Holy Ghoſt, repreſented by Water, is the principall of our regeneration. Alſo as Water doth fructifie the Earth, and make it fit to bear fruit, ſo the Holy Spirit bedewing our Souls, makes us capable to bring forth the fruit of good works. Moreover, as Water doth quench the thirſt, ſo the Holy Ghoſt doth quench the thirſt of earthly things. To which is referd that which our Saviour ſaith in St. <hi>John</hi> 7. <hi>If any one Thirſt, Let him come unto mee and drink.</hi> But certainly they who thruſt <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Similitudes into Baptiſm are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant in divers kinds. Water is uſed in Baptiſm, inaſmuch as it waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:169751:95"/>
and cleanſeth, not as it refreſheth, nor as it allayes the thirſt being drank. Otherwiſe wee ought to conſider it as drink, and confound the Baptiſm and the Euchariſt. Water is not conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Baptiſm, but as <hi>Waſhing.</hi> The other proprieties which it may have, are our of the Sacramentall analogy. If this Element ſhould have yet more qualities proper to repreſent the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, or the Holy Spirit, they are not of the Sacrament, and it is not for us to place them there.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="aphorisms">
            <pb facs="tcp:169751:95"/>
            <head>AN Epitome of this Treatiſe, compriſed in theſe Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſmes following.</head>
            <p>
               <label>I.</label>
MAny are learned in the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie of the Euchariſt, who nevertheleſs have not Knowledge e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of the grounds and myſteries of this Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <label>II.</label>
Many Treatiſes of Devotion, which have the vogue among the people, namely touching the holy Supper, ſerve rather to foment ignorance, than to augment inſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:169751:96"/>
               <label>III.</label>
They are ridiculous, who, endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſpecifie all the particular Cauſes of the Circumſtances of the Paſsion, give us Allegories for Reaſons, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphors for Myſteries.</p>
            <p>
               <label>IV.</label>
This ordinary Phraſe, the <hi>Altar of the Croſſe,</hi> is improper and ſubject to evill Conſequences.</p>
            <p>
               <label>V.</label>
The Hiſtoricall repreſentation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we call to mind a Man nayled to the Croſſe, is not this Act whereby Jeſus Chriſt is made preſent to ours Souls.</p>
            <p>
               <label>VI.</label>
The Reaſon why Jeſus Chriſt invites us to eat his Fleſh, and drink his Blood, is underſtood of very few, <hi>viz.</hi> why wee ought to drink his Blood, foraſmuch as it is the Blood of the New Teſtament; &amp; why from the Oblation of his Body we conclude the eating of it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:169751:96"/>
               <label>VII.</label>
The Reaſon conſiſts of Maxims op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to thoſe of the Old Teſtament. For the Law contained certain Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances which prohibited that which Jeſus Chriſt commands us in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>VIII.</label>
Jeſus Chriſt invites us to drink his Blood for the ſame reaſon which forbids us to eat blood. For the Law ſaith, Ye ſhall eat no blood; becauſe it is ſhed for the remiſsion of ſins. Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, Drink ye this Blood; becauſe it is ſhed for the remiſsion of ſins.</p>
            <p>
               <label>IX.</label>
It is a Maxim of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that none can eat of that which hath bin offered for him for remiſsion of ſins. But Jeſus Chriſt commands us to eat his Body given for our ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:169751:97"/>
               <label>X.</label>
In the Old Teſtament the Prieſts were to eat the Sacrifice, which they offered for the ſins of other men. But Jeſus Chriſt hath transferr'd this Rite to ſinners themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XI.</label>
The Communion to which Jeſus Chriſt invites us is marked with the names of two acts, whereof one is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the Ceremoniall Law, <hi>viz.</hi> to eat that which hath bin ſacrifiſed for our ſins; the other contrary to the Law of Nature, <hi>viz.</hi> to eat the fleſh of man.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XII.</label>
God had ordained that we ſhould not eat of any Blood, untill the Blood of Chriſt ſhould be ſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XIII.</label>
The Law forbidding Sinners to eat the Sacrifice of their Expiation, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:169751:97"/>
that the true Sacrifice was not yet exhibited, nor their Expiation accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XIV.</label>
In the Old Teſtament, the Eating of the Expiatory Sacrifice was a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotall Act, required for Expiation. But at this day this Eating is an effect of Expiation already made.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XV.</label>
In the Scripture the more a phraſe is remote from the ordinary Rules of the Language of men, the more myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious it is.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XVI.</label>
The Communion of the Body of Chriſt is repreſented by the act of Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, not ſimply by ſimilitude, but to retain the Term of this Teſtamentary Clauſe, which Jeſus Chriſt hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked in this Sacrament, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad man to eat the Sacrifice of his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piation. And this ſpeech means; That
<pb facs="tcp:169751:98"/>
the Communion of the Body of Chriſt is in effect that which the eating of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices was in Figure.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XVII.</label>
In the Life Naturall man and his meat are different Kinds; but in the Life Spirituall man and his nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ought to be of the ſame kind.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XVIII.</label>
The Old Teſtament had no force in compariſon of the New, becauſe the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtator was not yet dead.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XIX.</label>
Whereas death permits not any man to be Executor of his own Will, Jeſus Chriſt is riſen again to execute his.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XX.</label>
He who dyed firſt of all men, dyed of a bloody death. The death of Jeſus Chriſt was ſigned with blood.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:169751:98"/>
               <label>XXI.</label>
The firſt Blood which was ſhed on Earth and the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt are oppoſite one to the other in ſome reſpect.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXII.</label>
The firſt that felt death is alſo the firſt that ſacrifiſed with Blood, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the bloody Oblation of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXIII.</label>
The Blood, which was ſhed for one man alone, or for ſome ſmall number of perſons, never entred into the Holy Place; but only that which was ſhed for many; <hi>(i. e)</hi> for the multitude, or for the Church in generall. The Blood of Jeſus Chriſt hath pierced the Holy Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as having been ſhed for many.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXIV.</label>
That, which moved our Saviour to ordain Bread rather than Fleſh to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent his Body, is not becauſe that Fleſh hath ſerved heretofore in Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. For Bread and Wine were alſo employed in Legall Oblations. But it is,
<pb facs="tcp:169751:99"/>
that he would ſhew that after him no creature ſhould any more dye for the ſin of man. Therefore it is that he hath ordained Sacraments which require not the ſlaughter of any Creature, as being compounded of ſigns which are of themſelves without life, and of other ſubſtance than of fleſh and blood.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXV.</label>
All the properties of Bread and Wine enter not into the Analogy or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall relation which theſe Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have with the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt. Many ſimilitudes which the Learned introduce in this matter, are impertinent and abuſive, as when they repreſent the violent death of Jeſus Chriſt by the Baking of Bread in the Oven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>XXVI.</label>
God never repeats the ſame thing but it is with ſome diverſity. It is to the end that things which are obſcure in one place, may be made unto us intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible by another. This is the ſcope of the difference which is found among the
<pb facs="tcp:169751:99"/>
Evangeliſts, reciting the Inſtitution of the Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXVII.</label>
Before the Paſſeover there was no Sacramentall Eating. Jeſus Chriſt celebrated the firſt and the laſt Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Eating of his Body, <hi>viz.</hi> the Paſſeover and the Euchariſt on one and the ſame table.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXVIII.</label>
The Paſſeover that Jeſus Chriſt ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated is the ſeaventh and laſt of thoſe which are recited in the Scripture, as being the perfection and concluſion of all thoſe aforegoing. In this laſt Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over the true Lamb is there found in perſon. Moreover as the Paſſeover came from Egypt, there where it was firſt celebrated, ſo Jeſus Chriſt alſo was called out of Egypt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXIX.</label>
The Sacraments of the Chriſtian Church have already dured longer time than the Moſaicall Ceremonies have ſubſiſted.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:169751:100"/>
               <label>XXX.</label>
The Inſtitution of the Paſſeover is recited very largely, this of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt is compriſed in very few words. It is becauſe That contained many Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, This here but a very few. But finally the Inſtitution of the Paſſeover ſpeaks much more of the ſign than of the thing ſignified. This is the ſtyle of the Law to be prolix in the narration of Ceremonies, and to ſpeak very briefly of ſpirituall graces repreſented under ſuch figures.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXXI.</label>
The Sacraments of the Chriſtian Church were formed of matters and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions ſimple, naturall and Common; to the end that they might not be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto Change, but remain unvari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXXII.</label>
The difference of times, of places, and perſons, whereto God had bound the moſt notable Ceremonies of the Law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> tended to facilitate their abrogation. But on the Contrary, our Saviour hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:169751:100"/>
not prefixed any time for the Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Supper, to the end that it might be univerſally practiſed in all times and in all places.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXXIII.</label>
That in the Supper, Jeſus Chriſt is repreſented as he was on the Croſſe, and not as he is in Heaven, as dead, and not as glorified, this is, becauſe the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments tend rather to aſſure us of the glory that Jeſus Chriſt acquired unto us, than to deſcribe that which he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth himſelf. Now it is by his death that he hath gotten us this glory. From thence it comes, that, having Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted two Sacraments which repreſent him dead, he hath not ordained any one which might repreſent him glorified.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXXIV.</label>
That Our Saviour hath not Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more illuſtrious Signes, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why they are not miraculous, is, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other reaſons, foraſmuch as the end of Miracles is to ſhew the greatneſs and power of God: But, on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the end of our Sacraments, chiefly of
<pb facs="tcp:169751:101"/>
the Euchariſt, is to ſhew the infirmity, the death and humiliation of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXXV.</label>
According to the Maxims of the Roman Church, a man may, without thinking of it, and not knowing any thing of it, eat the Body of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXXVI.</label>
There is none of us who knows all the particular Reaſons of all the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Paſsion.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXXVII.</label>
That the Hiſtory of the Paſsion of Jeſus Chriſt doth not move us ſo much, as that of many others, whoſe afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are recited in Scripture, is, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the ſufferings of Jeſus Chriſt are not the Object of any naturall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, ſuch as we may have for other men, but of another kind of reſentment, which being Spirituall, is not ſo eaſie to be raiſed.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXXVIII.</label>
From thence it alſo comes that the ſuperſtitious are ſometimes more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb facs="tcp:169751:101"/>
at the rehearſall of the Paſsion of Jeſus Chriſt, than the true Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXXIX.</label>
Here we conſider why it hath been eaſier for many to reſolve to ſuffer death for the love of Chriſt, than to ſhed ſo much as one tear for the love of him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XL.</label>
Although the Spirituall Communion of the Body of Chriſt be a Super naturall Act, nevertheleſs it is not done by a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous tranſportation and raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Spirit, as was that of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XLI.</label>
A Roman Catholick hath need of much more time to learn his Religion, than an Orthodox to underſtand his. And particularly concerning the Euchariſt, An Orthodox man will ſooner learn all that he ought to know concerning it, than a Roman Catholick the tenth part of that which his Religion teacheth him concerning this point.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XLII.</label>
The ſtyle of the New Teſtament is
<pb facs="tcp:169751:102"/>
compoſed of ſix kinds of phraſes and termes of different originall; ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, others figurative.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XLIII.</label>
The Figurative Speeches which are in the New Teſtament, are drawn from five divers ſorts of matter.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XLIV.</label>
The Figure which is in this word <hi>[Eating]</hi> for to denote the Communion of the Body of Chriſt, is not ſimply de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the naturall Act of Eating in generall, but from the Action of the Faithfull of the Old Teſtament, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating of the Fleſh of Sacrifices, and other Sacred meats.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XLV.</label>
In the Old Teſtament there were but two other Holy, For they were exhibited either by Waſhing, or by Nouriſhment. Baptiſm and the Euchariſt doe anſwer to theſe two kinds of Actions. This i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Reaſon wherefore we have theſe two Sacraments, and in theſe two manners above-ſayd.</p>
            <trailer>FIN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>S.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:169751:102"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
